<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The summe of a sermon, preached at Sowthell the thirtith of March. 1596. By T.W.</title>
            <author>T. W. (Thomas Wilcox), 1549?-1608.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1597</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 112 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 38 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A15346</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 25630</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S111705</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99846985</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99846985</idno>
            <idno type="VID">11988</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A15346)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 11988)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1563:09)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The summe of a sermon, preached at Sowthell the thirtith of March. 1596. By T.W.</title>
                  <author>T. W. (Thomas Wilcox), 1549?-1608.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[74] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by the Widow Orwin, for Thomas Man,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1597.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>T.W. = Thomas Wilcox.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-E (A2-4 cancelled).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  16th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:11988:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:11988:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE SVMME OF A SERMON, PREA<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>CHED AT SOW<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>THELL THE THIR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tith of March. 1596.</p>
            <p>By <hi>T.W.</hi>
            </p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's or publisher's device</figDesc>
               <head>BY PEACE PLENTY. BY WISDOME PEACE</head>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON</hi> Printed by the Widow Orwin, for <hi>Thomas Man.</hi> 1597.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:11988:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:11988:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>Lord Ieſus begin, and make an end.</head>
            <head type="sub">A Sermon preached at Sowthell.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>THE TEXT. Matth. 11. verſ. 28. 29. 30.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p n="28">28 Come vnto me, all ye that are wearie and laden, and I will eaſe you.</p>
                  <p n="29">29 Take my yoke an you, and learne of me, that I am meeke and lowly in heart: and ye ſhall finde rest vnto your ſoules.</p>
                  <p n="30">30 For my yoke is eaſie, and my burden light.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HAT brother ſaid very well, who ere while out of this place told vs, that the exerciſes of this daye, are or ſhould bee the ſame to our ſoules, that phyſicke is to the body. The reaſon is, becauſe as many times medicines helpe cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall infirmities, ſo theſe holy and heauenly exerciſes of faſting, prayer, and preaching, ſhould heale the maladies of our mindes.
<pb facs="tcp:11988:3"/>Though theſe things be true, and we willingly acknowledge the euidency &amp; certainty of the ſame, in al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> parts &amp; peeces thereof, yet this al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo is no leſſe true or certaine, that as phyſitians for the body, notwithſtanding al their skill and experience, are ſometimes deceiued, in the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry particular ſicknes it ſelfe of their patients, and the cauſes of the ſame, and thereupon mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter many times matter that doth ſmal good, and if ſometimes it do not much hurt it is wel: ſo the miniſters and preachers of Gods holy word, ſometimes by meanes of the ignorance of the ſtate of the people, with whome they deale, ſometimes by partiall or corrupted re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects in themſelues, ſometimes by the wai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardnes and wickednes of the hearers, and ſometimes by one meanes, and ſometimes by another, do now and then propound that, that either is impertinent, or elſe vnprofitable: not ſure as in regarde of it ſelfe, being the Lordes trueth (for ſo it is alwaies good and holeſome) but as in reſpect of the people or perſons, to whome it is propounded, who either thorow careleſnes or prophanenes of heart, or ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther corruption lying lurking in themſelues, profit not thereby in knowledge, care, conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, or comfort. Howbeit becauſe we knowe there is this difference in particular, betwixt the bodily medicines for the outward man, and ſpirituall phyſicke for the ſoule, that that which is for the body muſt haue the preſent
<pb facs="tcp:11988:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>vſe, or be preſently vſed, otherwiſe it will doe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he patient no good, &amp; as in regard of it ſelfe, will mould and putrifie. But that which is for the ſoule, though it fall out as many times it doth indeed that it is not powerfull at the firſt, or for the time preſent, yet (as that that neuer will corrupt, but abide vnto eternall life) it may and no doubt ſhall bee profitable afterwards (for the word that is deliuered ſhall neuer goe forth in vaine) we are in that hope, and will in confidence thereof deliuer that, that God hath been pleaſed, not only by art, but by hart to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint vs withall.</p>
            <p>And to perſiſt a little in our begun metaphor or ſimilitude, of bodily phiſicke. You haue by the two firſt preachers been trauailed withall (though it were as a man may ſay, by bitter po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and byting medicines, I meane as in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of mans corrupted nature) for the purg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of bad humors, &amp; the curing of dangerous, yea deadly diſeaſes and wounds. Now as ſkil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and tender harted phyſitians and chirurgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, do after bitter purgations and biting plai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, miniſter ſome ſweet things, and as wee may ſay gentle and lenitiue ſalues, that by that meanes the patients may conceiue ſome hope of health, yea helpe and cure: ſo though in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience I think the moſt here, haue not preſent need of ſweet comfort (and yet what your caſe is or may be that way I knowe not) as who I feare me for all that is paſt, &amp; euen particularly
<pb facs="tcp:11988:4"/>for this daies exerciſe, are not humbled as you ſhould, yet wil I aſſay in loue, becauſe <hi>charity is not ſuspicious,</hi> and in hope that though pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently it bee not, yet in time to come it may bee fit for you, to my power vttermoſt to lay open, and to miniſter vnto you the comforts of God.</p>
            <p>In regarde whereof, and for the better per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of which duety, I haue choſen this preſent place read vnto you, for the better vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding whereof, I pray you marke that in the verſe that goeth next before theſe that wee haue read, Chriſt our Sauiour had in plaine and euident termes declared, that the fulnes of all good things both bodily and ſpirituall, for this life preſent &amp; that which is to come, were from the father communicated vnto him, <hi>That ſo of his fulnes wee might all receiue euen grace for grace.</hi> Which leaſt wee might ſuppoſe hee had propounded, as many vaine glorious men doe their glory &amp; glittering, their plate, wealth and ſubſtance, their wit, health, &amp; ſtrength, to ſhew what they haue, and ſo to hunt after eſtimation and credit thereby, and not to doe other men good, vnles it be to daſell their eyes, and to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maze their vnderſtandings, quickly as it were, not affected only but ouercome, with the ſight &amp; ſenſe of ſuch things: he doth in theſe words giue all to vnderſtand far otherwiſe, yea he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clareth the quite and cleane contrary: for hee ſheweth, that neither the greatnes, and excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencie
<pb facs="tcp:11988:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>of his owne glory, nor our owne poore and weake eſtate, nor any thing elſe in him or from our ſelues, ſhould hinder vs from co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming to him, and being made plentifull partakers thereof, but further vs rather: for where there is fulnes, &amp; the ſame offered vnto vs for our good, in comming being called to partake of it, we ſhall not loſe our labour: and where there are wants in our ſelues, we cannot (if we haue any ſenſe or feeling thereof) but feele a ſupply, and indeede receiue it to, when it is ſo freely offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. Now becauſe wee doe ſometimes from Chriſts perſon in the greatnes of it, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times from the wonderfull riches and excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie of grace that is in him, and ſometimes from our own beggery &amp; neede, gather argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of diſcouragements vnto our ſelues, &amp; ſo ſundry times lay ſtumbling blocks in our owne waies to hinder vs, from approaching to ſuch ſoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne good, our Sauiour laboreth to remoue all theſe impediments, and ſtones of offence whatſoeuer, and louingly inuiteth vs vnto him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, and freely offereth to make vs parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers of all his graces, in this ſweete and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable ſaying, <hi>Come vnto mee all yee that la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour and bee heauie laden, and I will refreſh you, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In which words or verſes there are contay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned two ſpeciall thinges to bee marked. Firſt graue exhortations, or holy commandements if you wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> Chriſt thereby prouoking and ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
<pb facs="tcp:11988:5"/>vs vp to come vnto him, &amp; theſe are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayned verſ. 28.29. which courſe he knew was neceſſary, as well becauſe many times we ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine things to be arbitrary, as alſo becauſe we are backward, by reaſon of our dulnes, general<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to euery good thing, and particularly to this, though it highly concerne our owne ſpirituall benefite. The ſecond is a weighty reaſon ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to thoſe exhortations or comma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dements, the better both to proue the truth of that Chriſt had ſaid, and alſo the more effectually to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade vs to walke in the obedience and prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe thereof, and this reaſon is comprehended, verſ. 30.</p>
            <p>True it is indeed, that the reaſon doth more ſpecially concerne the latter exhortation or commandement, as we ſhall ſhew hereafter if God will. Howbeit it may not improperly al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo in ſome ſort and ſenſe be applied and refer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vnto the firſt. But becauſe this is not a poynt greatly materiall now, we wil let it paſſe and proceede to more neceſſary matter.</p>
            <p>Now concerning the exhortations or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements, they are according to the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the verſes in which they are contayned, two. And yet if I bee not deceiued, both of them tending to one ende, namely by calling men, to come vnto Chriſt, and to learne of him to miniſter comfort of conſcience to them that were heauie harted. And yet we muſt not thinke, that they are needles tautologies, or
<pb facs="tcp:11988:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>mine repetitions, but ſerue as to expreſſe Chriſts ſingular loue, towards afflicted per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, he vrging them as we ſee againe and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine: ſo to let vs vnderſtand, in the doubling and trebling of theſe ſweete and comfortable exhortations or commaundements, that it is no eaſie thing to comfort a wounded ſpirit, and that a broken and troubled heart, doth not by and by, though gladly it would, admit and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celue comfort. For if that were ſo, one exhorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, commaundement, call or promiſe, would ſuffice, but rather that euen for their mind, that is true in them, that is ſaid in the Prophet Iere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miah, and is repeated in this Euangeliſt chap. 2 <hi>Rahel weeping for her children, and would not be comforted, becauſe they were not.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And yet further betweene theſe two exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations or commaundements I make this diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, that in the firſt he calleth vs ſimply, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any other reſpect, than of our owne miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries and his mercies, to come vnto him for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leefe. And in the other he calleth on vs, or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandeth vs to learne of him, and to profit by our comming, and not to bee as bad ſchollers, that haue very good teachers or maiſters, and yet learne little or nothing from them. And we are further to marke, that in deliuerie of theſe exhortations or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandements, Chriſt obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth this order. Firſt he putteth downe the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation or commandement it ſelfe, as ver. 28 <hi>Come vnto me alye, &amp;c.</hi> &amp; ver. 29. <hi>Take my yoke
<pb facs="tcp:11988:6"/>vpon you, &amp;c.</hi> And then addeth promiſes, full of comfort and conſolation, as, <hi>I will refreſh you,</hi> in the end of verſ. 28. and againe, <hi>Ye ſhall find rest vnto your ſoules,</hi> the laſt words of verſe 29. which our Sauiour Chriſt preſſeth as wee ſee by doubling of them, not ſo much to expreſſe the infinite treaſure of ſpirituall ioye that is in him, as to aſſure vs that comming at his call, we ſhall haue that in great meaſure and plenty be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed vpon vs, that ſhall eaſe our ſmart. But all theſe things with many other moe, we ſhall ſee more plainely and vnderſtand: more fully in the particular expoſition of the words them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues as they lye in the text, and in the obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation of doctrines, ariſing out of them. To them therefore we come.</p>
            <p>Verſe. 28. It is ſaide, <hi>Come vnto me</hi>) In this verſe, two things contained: Firſt, the exhorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or commandement it ſelfe in theſe words, <hi>Come vnto me, &amp;c.</hi> Secondly, a promiſe adioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned as for our greater incouragement to well dooing, ſo for the better aſſurance of it in our hearts, in theſe words, <hi>And I will refreſh you, or make you to rest and find eaſe.</hi> In the exhortati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or commandement, we are to conſider the perſon exhorting or commaunding which is Chriſt, comfortably ſaying, <hi>Come vnto me:</hi> and the perſons exhorted or commaunded in theſe words, <hi>all ye that labour, &amp;c.</hi> who are deſcribed by adiuncts or attributes, ſetting out their mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable eſtate: and they are two, to wit, <hi>labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
<pb facs="tcp:11988:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>and being heauy laden.</hi> And indeede the promiſe following reſpecteth alſo theſe two perſons, that is to ſay, Chriſts perſon promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to refreſh, and the labouring or heauy la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, who are to be refreſhed.</p>
            <p>The word <hi>Come,</hi> whether it be of exhorting or commaunding, doth not comprehend in it, either readines, willingnes or power of them that are called, as of themſelues, as the Pelagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans in former times ſuppoſed, and our popiſh aduerſaries haue dreamed of late, becauſe we know the ſcripture ſaith, <hi>it is God that worketh in vs both the will and the deede according to his good pleaſure:</hi> and we beleeue that to be true, that our Sauiour Chriſt himſelfe teſtifieth ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>No man can come vnto mee, vnles the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther draw him:</hi> but rather the ſingular care and loue of the caller, and that not ſo much for his owne glory (who in the death and deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of men can get &amp; will get himſelfe a name) as for our good, who when we thinke no ſuch thing, no nor of our owne good neither, being diſtreſſed in ſpirit (for then commonly we are eyther dull and heauy hearted, or elſe thorow feare are grieuouſly caſt downe, and diſquieted in our ſelues) doth yet notwithſtanding call vpon vs and to vs, &amp; willeth vs to goe or come, not to others, for then we might imagine, ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that he had no power or will in himſelfe, or that he meant to ſhift vs off: &amp; beſides they eyther cannot or will not yeeld vs reliefe, if we
<pb facs="tcp:11988:7"/>ſhould repayre vnto them, but vnto himſelfe, yea to himſelfe alone, and no others with him, for ſo much doe I take theſe words, <hi>vnto mee,</hi> to import.</p>
            <p>And that this is the true meaning indeede, both places of Scripture, and reaſons drawne from religion doe plainely proue. In the xiiii. of Hoſea, the Lord by the Prophet ſpeaketh thus vnto the people. <hi>O Iſrael returne vnto the Lord thy God,</hi> as though he ſhould ſay, to him onely, and to none other beſides or with him. To the ſame end, yea and worthy to be noted, as ſeruing alſo for confirmation and expoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, of all the words of this very verſe, tendeth that which Chriſt himſelfe ſaith, Iſaiah 55. which no man doubteth to be an euident pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecie of Chriſt and the graces, that we ſhall finde in him, if with a liuely and ſtedfaſt faith, we labour to lay hold of him, <hi>Encline your care &amp; come vnto me, heare and your ſoule ſhall liue, &amp; I wil make an euerlaſting couenant with you, euen the ſure mercies of Dauid.</hi> And ſo much indeed muſt Chriſts words import, both there and here, or elſe we ſhall ſee a more dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous conſequence than we thinke of. For if any were to be reſpected beſides him or ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with him in that worke of ſpirituall ioy. then were he not God all-ſufficient, becauſe if any were ioyned with him, he were not ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent of himſelfe: and, if he were not the <hi>God of all comfort,</hi> as well as the <hi>Father of mercies,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:11988:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>he were not God indeede, and ſo our fayth &amp; the grounds of the word or Chriſtian religion ſhould be ſhaken. Beſides if it were ſo, and he told vs not of it, but as a vaine glorious perſon would take all to himſelfe, and more indeede then did belong vnto him, then ſhall hee bee wrapped vp in a double tranſgreſſion, the one againſt his father, towards whom he hath ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried himſelfe vnfaithfully, whileſt he hath not reuealed vnto vs all his counſels communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vnto him for our good: and the other to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards man, becauſe he hath dealt deceitfully with vs, in that he hath depriued vs of hope &amp; helpe, that we might haue from others with or beſides him. But all theſe things are moſt falſe and vntrue: for <hi>he was the faithfulleſt in all the houſe of God, euen as a ſonne,</hi> and comming out of the Fathers boſome, hath communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vnto vs all his counſels, and we knowe and beleeue that <hi>there was neuer guile found in his mouth.</hi> And therefore that ſenſe muſt of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitie be true, yea the onely true ſenſe. It fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth in the verſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>All ye that labour and are heauy laden.</hi> As the former words reſpected the perſon calling and exhorting or commaunding vs to come vnto him, ſo theſe words concerne them that are called, exhorted or commaunded. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in Chriſt firſt ſheweth, that he is free from all partiality or reſpect of perſons, in as much as indefinitely or generally hee calleth all heauie
<pb facs="tcp:11988:8"/>heartes, and as it were commandeth them to repayre vnto him. Which doth not onely ſerue to ſhew his great care and loue towards them, whileſt he both calleth them all, and calleth them when they thinke leaſt of any ſuch mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter (for if we would reſpect him in his mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificence, or men in their owne vnworthines, what are they that ſhould receiue any fauour, ſpecially ſo great a grace as this?) but alſo an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwereth that, that many diſtreſſed ſpirits ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine that God hath promiſed or ſhewed fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour to ſuch and ſuch, becauſe of ſome rare &amp; ſingular grace in them, and not for his owne mercies ſake, or for their miſerable diſtreſſed eſtate. But he that will well weigh the courſe of Gods workes that way, or the trueth of the word, he ſhall find this to be but an imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of mans heart and head, or a ſuggeſtion and temptation of Satan, rather to hinder the courſe and paſſage of Gods grace and good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, from troubled and afflicted ſoules. For as for Gods mercies, they are and muſt bee alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether free, or elſe they are not mercies. For who knoweth not that man in his beſt eſtate after regeneration, cannot merit the meaneſt mercies of God, not in thinges appertayning to this life, no not in a crumme of bread, or droppe of water, much leſſe ſpirituall graces and eternall life. And though it be true that God acknowledgeth his owne graces in his owne ſeruants, as the fruits of their fayth, and
<pb facs="tcp:11988:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>good teſtimonies of their willing obedience, yet he may if he will by reaſon of the imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection that cleaueth thereto reiect all. And no doubt would doe it, as in regard of his ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute and exact iuſtice, but that he hath proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in Chriſt as a gracious meanes for the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giueneſſe of all our ſinnes thorow his death, ſo a plentifull ſupply of whatſoeuer is wanting in vs, thorow the moſt perfect righteouſnes that is in him.</p>
            <p>And me thinketh we may ſee this to be true, thorough the diſclaime that Gods people haue made of all, or any good thing in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, as Dauid for example in the xvi. Pſalm. <hi>My goodnes, O Lord, reacheth not vnto thee:</hi> &amp; Iſaiah for himſelfe &amp; all the faithful, Chap. 64. <hi>Our righteouſneſſes before thee, are as filthie &amp; ſtained cloathes.</hi> Yea wee may ſee it by the courſe they haue kept, in powring foorth of prayers vnto God, in which they haue reſpec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ſimply and onely theſe two thinges, Gods mercy and their owne miſerie, and vſed them as principall arguments, both to vphold their owne hearts, and to prouoke him to pittie, as wee may playnly ſee in many Pſalmes of Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid, but ſpecially in the 86. thorowout. So that we may ſafely ſay, God reſpecteth nothing in man, no not his miſerie (though I doubt not but that many times he is much moued there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with) for if it were ſo, he ſhould either leaue all or none in miſerie, and that our owne expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience
<pb facs="tcp:11988:9"/>teacheth vs the contrary: or if mans mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery ſhould be the working cauſe in him, then thoſe that are moſt miſerable, ſhould ſooneſt and moſt of all be reſpected, but that is not v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riuerſally true neither. And againe, if miſery ſhould be the firſt mouing cauſe in God, why doeſt not thou that art diſtreſſed, and in thine owne iudgement ſo much as no man before thee, from thine owne eſtate and confeſſion, gather comfort vnto thy ſelfe from the Lorde? Wherefore let the troubled ſpirit caſt away theſe conceits, and fully aſſure himſelfe that as in no reſpect, <hi>God is a reſpecter of perſons,</hi> ſo not in diſtributing and beſtowing his graces, ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally ſpirituall graces. And that therefore ſo often as this or ſuch like thoughtes come into their heads, they ſhould know that they are, either fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ignorance or diffidence of their owne ſoules, or from the malice of Satan a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them, and therefore they ſhould beware how they admit the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, for men can hardly carry ſuch fire in their breaſts and not be burnt. But let vs proceede.</p>
            <p>Leaſt this generall and indefinite tearme of our Sauiour, ſhould be ſtretched further than his meaning, hee knowing alſo euen wicked men to be more forward that way then they ought, he doth reſtrayne it, by two particular adiuncts or attributes ſaying <hi>(yee that labour, and are heauy laden)</hi> Where firſt wee are to marke, that as in other places of the Scriptures,
<pb facs="tcp:11988:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>and other caſes alſo, God is wont to reſemble ſpirituall things by bodily, and to ſpeake of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by metaphoricall and borrowed kind of ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches; whether they be things in himſelfe, or without him: ſo here he doth the like, for vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der theſe termes of <hi>labouring and being heauy laden,</hi> which are properly referred to outward actions and bodily burdens, he meaneth ſenſe of ſinne, conflict of conſcience, and tugging and wreſtling as it were, with and vnder the wrath of God, ſometimes in outward afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, ſometimes in inward ſorrow, yea &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation for the ſame. And as this is an v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuall thing with the ſpirit of God, here and in other places of Scripture, &amp; namely Iſaiah 55. ſaying: <hi>Ho euery one that thirsteth, come yee vnto the waters, &amp; yee that haue no ſiluer come buy &amp; cat, come I ſay, buy wine and milke, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſiluer, and without money,</hi> vnderſtanding there by <hi>thirſt</hi> that which he doth in this place by <hi>labour and burdening,</hi> and by <hi>water, wine, and milke,</hi> that which he doth by <hi>refreſhing &amp; eaſe:</hi> ſo he doth it not without cauſe, ſpecially as in regard of vs, who doe not onely vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand outward things better than inward, but voleſſe that we be taught of the inward by the outward, we can hardly comprehend them. He not meaning vnder theſe borrowed termes, to ſignifie that theſe outward are able to the full, and as it were liuely to ſet out the inward and ſpirituall <hi>(for that no eye hath ſeene, no
<pb facs="tcp:11988:10"/>eare hath heard, no heart can conceiue, nor tongue can vtter)</hi> but by them ſo well ſorting with our nature, to giue vs ſome ſight, ſmacke or taſte of them. And euen herein alſo ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth Chriſts loue, that he is pleaſed to ſtoop downe ſo low vnto vs, and in ſuch baſe termes to expreſſe vnto vs ſuch excellent things.</p>
            <p>But yet let vs a little more particularly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine the words. That word that is here ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med <hi>labour,</hi> doth not ſignifie ſimply euery la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, but ſuch a labour as is ſore, and hath ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with it toyling of the body, and moyling of the mind, with carke and care, yea and wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rines both of body and mind ioyned with it as an effect flowing from it, and that cauſeth ſome alſo to turne it thus, <hi>Come vnto me all ye that are weary.</hi> Whatſoeuer it be, we may ſee, that Chriſt mindeth by this Metaphore, to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe this much vnto vs, that diſtreſſe of ſpirit vpon what cauſe ſoeuer it ariſe, and conflict of conſcience, is no ſmall payne, but a great and grieuous ſorrow, entring deepe into the ſoule, diſquieting the ſpirit, diſtempering the body, and making all parts and powers vnfit for al or any duety almoſt. And this to be true, the Scripture elſewhere ſheweth it, and namely Prou. 18. Where it ſayth. <hi>The ſpirit of a man may indure his infirmitie, but a wounded ſpirite who ſhall beare it?</hi> And our owne experience can witnes it, if eyther wee haue beene hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled our ſelues, or haue beene acquainted with
<pb facs="tcp:11988:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>other mens ſorrowes that way: in whome it hath taken away for the time, ſleepe from the eyes, hearing from the eares, ſpeech from the mouth, appetite from the ſtomacke: nay I wil ſay more, it hath cauſed ſome, to aſſay the fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing of their payne, as they ſuppoſed, with a ſhameful &amp; feareful end had it bin accompli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed. Which yet notwithſtanding is not ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken here, or propounded elſewhere vnto vs in the word, to diſcourage or oppreſſe them that be in that combate: but as on the one ſide, to teach all men to caſt away ſecuritie and care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſnes, ſo on the other ſide to inſtruct them that are ſo weake in themſelues to relie vpon him that is the God of their ſtrength, who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in them and with them, and for them, will doubtleſſe make his ſtrength and power to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare in their weakenes.</p>
            <p>That other word <hi>heauie laden,</hi> is metapho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricall alſo and tranſlated from bodily burdens vnto ſpirituall, that is to ſay, to the burdens of ſinne and iniquitie, which lye more hard vpon the ſoule and ſpirit, though worldly men feele them not, than any outward doth or can vpon the bodie: yea though a man ſhould be preſſed therewithall vnto death, becauſe that onely reacheth vnto the bodie, and in the middeſt of the paynes thereof, the ſoule little or nothing touched, nay, it may bee very cheerefull and comfortable ſpiritually, and ſo cauſe the ſoule almoſt to finde no griefe, as in the Martyrs, that
<pb facs="tcp:11988:11"/>haue beene ſo many wayes, and ſo grieuouſly tormented, may and doth appeare: but when the ſoule is ouerclogged with ſinne and the ſenſe thereof, or of Gods anger againſt it for the ſame, the very body is tainted thereby with ſundry ſorts of ſickneſſes, and diuers kindes of diſeaſes, ſome recouerable and ſome vnreco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerable.</p>
            <p>And we ſhall find it much vſed in the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, that ſinne it ſelfe is compared vnto a bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then, which may in part appeare not onely by this, when the Prophets call the iudgements of God, that ſhould fal vpon men for their ſinnes, <hi>burthens,</hi> that ſo there might be ſome proporti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on betweene the iniquitie they had commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, &amp; the puniſhment that was executed vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them for it: but alſo by a plaine place of the Prophet Dauid, in that eight &amp; thirtie Pſalme, that wee ſung before this Sermon, when hee ſayth: <hi>Mine iniquities are gone ouer my head, and as a weightie burden they are too heauie for mee to beare.</hi> By all which we may ſee, that ſin is not ſo ſleight or light a matter, as men make it, but a wonderfull weight indeede, whether wee conſider it in it owne nature, as being the feareful violation &amp; breach of the law of God; or God that is offended thereby, <hi>whoſe pure eies cannot behold that that is euill,</hi> &amp; his hand in iuſtice is preſt and ready to ſtrike, or the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers &amp; dammages they pull vpon themſelues, in body and in ſoule, for this life preſent, and
<pb facs="tcp:11988:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>for that which is to come: as terror and feare of heart, ſhame and confuſion of face, diſcredite amonſt men, ſpecially godly, diſcords yea anarchies in Kingdomes, common wealthes and families, and what not?</p>
            <p>And indeede this were a point well worth the wading into, by reaſon of the groſſenes and corruption of the age wherein we liue, making ſo ſmal or no conſcience at all of ſinne and tranſgreſsion, were it not that we are to be occupied in ſome other points of comfort and conſolation. Howbeit this much we may ſay, that as it argueth ſmall conſcience of ſinne in men, that mittigate &amp; minſe it; ſo it miniſtreth ſmall hope of comfort vnto themſelues or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, of the happie recouery out of it. For how is it likely, that they ſhould be cured of a diſeaſe, that eyther knowe it not, or feele it not, or take it not to be ſo deadly and dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous as it is? Whereas on the other ſide the tender conſcience charging, yea ſurcharging it ſelfe, with more then it ſhould, it may be (&amp; yet that can hardly be, if men conſider right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the height and the haynouſnes, yea the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finiteneſſe &amp; innumerableneſſe of their owne ſinnes generall and particular) though in that accuſation it ſuffer much griefe, yea, &amp; plunge it ſelfe as it were into diſtruſtfulnes, is in more hope of a gracious recouerie (which in the midſt of ſuch ſorrow of heart ſhould miniſter ſome comfort) becauſe ſinne felt is more like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb facs="tcp:11988:12"/>by repentance to be cured and healed, then that that men make no keepe or account of. But to let this point paſſe, and to come to that that doth more nighly concerne our purpoſe at this preſent.</p>
            <p>Now there followeth the laſt wordes of this 28. verſe: <hi>And I will refreſh you,</hi> and containe in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſecond part thereof, namely a ſweet &amp; comfortable promiſe for the better drawing yea alluring of vs, vnto him that calleth vs vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to himſelfe, but yet for our ſpirituall good. A thirſtie body indeede woulde reioyce to heare, though it were but of water and not of drinke, to ſlake the thirſt withall: the reaſon is, becauſe he knoweth it, and taketh it, to be a meane to maintayne life. The tydings of eaſe, and ligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of him in ſome ſort of a great and grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous burden, to him that carrieth it, is no doubt of it gladſome and ioyfull alſo, becauſe it is a toyle and a moyle, a weariſomnes and weakneſſe to body and minde to beare a waight (yea though it be but ſmall) continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally. Reaſon &amp; our owne experience teacheth vs the trueth hereof, in theſe worldly thinges. But how much more ſhall this be found true, as in regard of cooling yea ſatisfiyng our ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall drougth, or as in reſpect of eaſing the griefes and burdens of our mindes: which in deed ſhall be ſo much the better welcome vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs, when God ſhall be pleaſed in mercy to vouchſaue vs the ſame, by how much the bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens
<pb facs="tcp:11988:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>that we beare, and the paines we indure, are indeed grieuous, and (as wee may ſay and ſhall finde it too, without grace and aſsiſtance from God) vnbeareable. In theſe outwarde matters, the more that is promiſed the better we like, and the more great and faithfull the party is that giueth vs his word, the more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly we aſſure our ſelues: but if together with words, we finde vndeceiueable accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, then is our ioy, as a man may ſay, at the toppe and full. Marke theſe thinges here, and then we ſhall ſee our comfort increaſed.</p>
            <p>Where are more bountifull promiſes of truth and life then thoſe that euery where ſou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d in the holy Scripture? Doe not they reach to the good things of this life preſent, and that which is to come eſpecially? Who more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent than the Lorde that hath made them? Who more great for power? Who more cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine for good will? Who more aſſured for faſtneſſe and fidelity than he? Should not all theſe rayſe vp our ſpirits in our ſelues, that are fallen downe within vs, and euen as it were cauſe vs <hi>in hope or vnder hope, to beleeue againſt hope?</hi> Which that we may the better perceiue in our ſelues, and perſwade our hearts of, let vs a little inſiſt or ſtand vpon the words.</p>
            <p>He ſayth, and <hi>I will refreſh you.</hi> Who ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth it? He that eyther cannot or will not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme it? no verely. But Chriſt God and man in one perſon, conſiſting yet notwithſtanding
<pb facs="tcp:11988:13"/>of two ſeuerall and diſtinct natures, the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head and the manhood, hath deliuered it, that ſo we might be well aſſured, as of his eternall power by reaſon of his godhead, ſo of his infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite good will, by reaſon of his humanitie, and in both of them inſeparably ioyned together from the time of his conception, perſwade our hearts for the faithfull accompliſhment of this moſt gracious and ſweete promiſe. And wee muſt needes referre it to, and vnderſtand it of his whole perſon, not onely becauſe in him conſiſteth <hi>the fulnes of all goodnes</hi> as we haue heard, yea, <hi>euen the very fulnes of the godhead bodily,</hi> but alſo becauſe that deliuering this as the King, Prieſt, and Prophet of his Church, and not accompliſhing any of theſe offices, in eyther of his diſtinct natures ſeuerally, but in his whole perſon, he muſt in his perſon needes both deliuer this ſweete and comfortable pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, and alſo effectually performe the ſame in the hearts of his ſaythfull people.</p>
            <p>The word <hi>refreſh</hi> is metaphoricall, and well anſwereth indeede the tearmes before going, of <hi>labouring and being heauy laden.</hi> A man that laboureth ſore woulde bee glad of eaſe: who doubteth of that? The party that hath a ſore burthen on his backe would willingly be ligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. Nature, reaſon, experience &amp; all teacheth the trueth of this. How much more then hee, that is preſſed if not depreſſed with the ſight of ſinne, with the beholding of his owne in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmities,
<pb facs="tcp:11988:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>with the feeling and feare of Gods wrath againſt him for the ſame, would be glad to find refreſhing, eaſe, and comfort. Which if it be offred and meant as here it is, is excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent: but if it be receyued and felt, is ſo much the more notable, by how much the ſoule is better then the body, &amp; the griefes of the one more great then the other, and therefore they being holpen and cured, the mercy miniſtred and made effectuall, and the comforts flowing therefrom, farre ſurpaſſing all. Wherein our Sauiour Chriſt ſurely offreth no more, then what hee is able to performe, nay, then that which he will accompliſh indeed, ſo that wee labour by that eye of fayth, which he hath bin pleaſed to vouchſaue vnto vs, and that hand of fayth that he hath beſtowed vpon vs, ſted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſtly to looke vpon it, to lay hold of it, and to applie it to our owne ſoules, becauſe the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes of God, though moſt holy, heauenly, &amp; excellent in themſelues, yet without fayth to feele and apply the ſame vnto our hearts, they are as in regarde of men, as if they were not at all.</p>
            <p>And yet to ſay trueth, and that indeede for the further inlarging of the comfort of diſtreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed conſciences, wee are to marke, that the word ſignifieth much more then <hi>refreſhing:</hi> though I deny not but that that conſidered, as it commeth from God, or in it owne ſelfe, is a very ſingular grace. And it ſhall both ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare,
<pb facs="tcp:11988:14"/>and be ſo much the more gracious, by how much all and euery one of vs, are vnwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of it, yea moſt worthy of all diſcomfort &amp; iudgement, both for the time preſent and all continuance. But to the word, I ſay, it being compounded of a prepoſition or particle, and a verbe that ſignifieth to finiſh, ende or ceaſe from, our Sauiour noteth not onely refreſhing from the paynes, and pangues that we indure, but putting an ende vnto all troubles, and ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes that are vpon vs, whether they be out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward or inward, which though it ſhal be prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally, yea onely and moſt abſolutely perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med in the life that is to be reueiled, according to that of the ſpirit in the xiiii. of the Reuela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. <hi>Bleſſed are the dead that dye in the Lord, for they ceaſe from their labors, and their works follow them:</hi> yet it is in manner and meaſure be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gunne here, &amp; by fayth we ſtedfaſtly beleeue the full fruition of it, and thorowe hope holde faſt, and with patience looke for, the continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all enioying thereof And no doubt of it our Sauiour hath vſed ſo ſignificant a word, that he might the better prouide for, and propounde comfort to the wounded ſpirit, which as it is in anguiſh and griefe for the preſent diſtreſſe, ſo doth it trouble and torment it ſelfe, with this temptation, that it ſeeth no ende of the miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries and calamities thereof. But be not diſmai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſayth Chriſt, for the time ſhall come fayth Chriſt, wherein I will <hi>wipe all teares from your
<pb facs="tcp:11988:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>eyes,</hi> all griefe from your heartes, all ſorrowe from your ſoules and not onely ſtay there, but giue you perpetuall <hi>reſt with them that are ſanctified,</hi> and ſaued thorow me.</p>
            <p>Hitherto we haue tranailed, and I truſt not vnprofitably, chiefly in the expoſition of the words, interlacing now and then ſome things of comfort and conſolation, no whit I am ſure ſtrange from the meaning of Chriſt, or impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per or vnfitte for this preſent exerciſe and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly. Now it remayneth, that before we go any further in the wordes of our text, we doe from this verſe gather ſome ſuch good leſſons, as it doth afford vs, for doctrine or conſolatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; becauſe this indeed may moſt properly be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the life of the word, when men learne from the ſame good inſtructions, and indeuour to make good and profitable vſe thereof.</p>
            <p>The firſt point of doctrine iſſuing out of this text is this, that true and ſound comfort for an afflicted conſcience is no where els, eyther to be ſought or found, but in leſus Chriſt onely. Where I beſeech you firſt to marke, both how this doctrine ariſeth from hence, and then the tearmes in which I doe propound and deliuer the ſame. It is gathered from this place, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe our Sauiour calleth vs vnto him yea vnto him alone, which if it had not bin the will of his Father, and verie truth indeede, or if hee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone had not had aboundant, yea infinite mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of ſtrong and ſolide comfort in himſelfe,
<pb facs="tcp:11988:15"/>he would neuer haue done, as we haue already heard in the beginning of this exerciſe. And for the wordes I doe not ſay, there is no com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort to bee founde: for meate, drinke, ſleepe, friends, recreation, and ſuch like, are comforts I confeſſe, but not true and ſound comfort, for a diſtreſſed ſpirit. For the affliction of the mind is inward, and theſe are but outward, &amp; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore are not fitte for a perſon or partie ſo affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: and I would as ſoone thinke and ſay, that bodily food were the proper and ſound nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhment of the ſoule, as ſuppoſe that theſe outward things, were the true and ſound com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of a broken and contrite heart. But that yet wee may bee the better perſwaded of the trueth of this point, let vs proceed vnto ſome further proofes of it.</p>
            <p>This was not in my mind obſcurely ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, vnder all the ſacrifices of the old law, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they were ordinarie, or extraordinarie, dayly or yearly, generall or particular, all and euery one of them, in meaſure more or leſſe, tending ſtill vnto him, whom they did prefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure and ſignifie, as the Apoſtle at large decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth in the Epiſtle to the Hebrewes. And why him becauſe he was he alone, <hi>in whom God was pleaſed to reconcile the world vnto himſelfe,</hi> and to make the one and onely obiect of our faith. And this is plainely propounded vnto vs and proued alſo, by manifolde texts of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture both in the old and new teſtament. I wil
<pb facs="tcp:11988:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>not trouble you with many, for I like not much of that courſe. Out of that great ſtore let vs take two or three both playne and pregnant for this purpoſe. In the 55. Chapter of the booke of the Prophet Iſaiah, a place cited be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, and is as we all know and confeſſe an eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent prophecie concerning Chriſt, and the graces that wee ſhall finde in him, if with a liuely and ſtedfaſt fayth we labour to lay hold of him, it is ſayd, <hi>Encline your eare and come vnto mee</hi> (Oh marke how like this Euangeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Prophet &amp; our Sauiour himſelfe ſpeake &amp; let this phraſe alſo I beſeech you ſerue for a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation and expoſition of theſe wordes of our text) <hi>Heare and your ſoule ſhall liue: and I will make an euerlaſting couenant with you, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen the ſure mercies of Dauid.</hi> Euery worde hath his waight, he, yea, he alone will eſtabliſh not a momentany, but an euerlaſting coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant with all his faithfull, of which that wee might be the better certified, hee telleth vs it ſhall be ſure, yea, as ſure as the mercies mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted vnto, and beſtowed vpon Dauid, which as they were large and almoſt innumerable, ſo were they irreuocable and could neuer fayle. To the ſame purpoſe ſerueth a notable ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of the Apoſtle 2. Cor. 1.5. <hi>As the ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings of Chriſt abound in vs, ſo our conſolation aboundeth thorow Christ.</hi> By ſufferinges of Chriſt, he meaneth not onely thoſe thinges, that we indure at the hands of perſecuters for
<pb facs="tcp:11988:16"/>Chriſtes ſake: for Chriſt did not onely ſuffer that way, but euen thoſe anguiſhes alſo, that we haue in our ſoules and in our ſpirits, Chriſt being as much, yea, farre more throwne down and humbled that way than all fleſh, as appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth by his conflict in the garden, and by his outcries vpon the Croſſe, ſaying: <hi>My God, my God, why haſt thou forſaken mee.</hi> And though theſe haue bin, were, and are, very good in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed (as thoſe that haue felt and doe feele the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, know and confeſſe) yet to the ende that wee might aſſure our ſelues, that our ioyes ſhoulde match them, he ſayth, <hi>Our conſolations abound thorow him.</hi> For if there were not a proporti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on betwixt our heauines and our comfort, nay I will ſay more, a ſuperaboundance of our ioyes aboue our griefes, then ſure, what by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of Satans malice againſt vs, and the dul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and hardneſſe of our owne heartes to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue, and the greatneſſe of our griefes &amp; ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows beſides, it would goe hard with a diſtreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed ſpirit. And therefore as for the comforting of vs, againſt the hugenes and height of our ſinnes, we ſay with the Apoſtle, <hi>where ſinne hath abounded there grace hath ouerabounded.</hi> So in this caſe of inward afflictions, particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly we ſay, our ſorrowes may be ſore and our griefes great, yet <hi>our light affliction, which is but for a moment, cauſeth vnto vs a farre moſt excellent and eternall waight as of glory</hi> in the life to come, ſo of ioy in this life rayſed vp in
<pb facs="tcp:11988:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>our hearts by the comfortable feeling thereof.</p>
            <p>And he that knoweth ſoundly, and feeling<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly beleeueth, the names, natures, perſon and offices of our Sauiour Chriſt, together with the effects that from him in them are commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicated to vs, cannot chuſe but ſee, feele, and confeſſe the trueth of this point. Hee is good, &amp; in him there is not, or cannot be any thing, but that which is abſolutely good, as in whoſe face and preſence alſo, there is the <hi>fulnes of ioy for euermore, and at his right hand pleaſures for euer and euer.</hi> He is likewiſe ſo good, that yet notwithſtanding he is man like vnto vs in eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry reſpect, <hi>ſinne onely excepted,</hi> and one that hath bin touched with the feeling of our infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities, by meanes whereof we may the more boldly come <hi>vnto the throne of grace, &amp; ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue mercy, and finde grace to helpe in time of neede.</hi> Yea, theſe two natures are ſo ioyned &amp; knit (as we may ſay) inſeparably in one per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, euen from the very time of his bleſſed co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception in the wombe of his mother, for the accompliſhment of the worke of our redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and our full comfort thereby, as that they cannot be deuided or ſundred, hee being man that ſo hee might ſuffer, and God that ſo hee might ouercome, the perfection and full ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhment of our redemption ſtanding vpon theſe two partes, ſuffering for ſinne: this is the firſt, and then ouercomming ſinne, and <hi>death, &amp; him that had the power of death, that
<pb facs="tcp:11988:17"/>is the deuill.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And why is he called Ieſus? but becauſe as it is ſayd Matth. 1. <hi>He ſhould ſaue his people from their ſinnes.</hi> For ſinne, and that that inſueth vpon ſinne, as ſhame and confuſion of face, horror of heart, condemnation &amp;c. is it that moſt ſtingeth mens mindes and ſoules. Now all theſe beeing taken away in Chriſt, why ſhould they not as well and comfortably ſing that tryumphant ſong, <hi>O death where is thy ſting? O graue or hell where is thy victory? the sting of death is ſinne, and the ſtrength of ſinne is the law. But thankes be vnto God, which hath giuen vs victory, thorow our Lord Ieſus Christ:</hi> as well as mournefully vtter that ſorrowfull voyce, <hi>Wretched man that I am, who ſhall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuer me from the body of this death!</hi> His other name Chriſt, and his ſtately offices, of King, Prieſt, and Prophet, contayned in it, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der it ſet out vnto vs, what doe they elſe, but proue this point? For why was he all in all, but to giue vs to vnderſtand that as all was in him, ſo all muſt be fette from him, or elſe it coulde no where be ſound. And though it bee true that diuers perſons had as ſome one or other of thoſe names (for example Iehoſhua) ſo one or diuers of thoſe offices vpon them, at one &amp; the ſelfe ſame time (as Melchiſedech if you will) yet neither had they all, or if they had them, they had them but as figures of him, whoſe perſon and place they did for a while
<pb facs="tcp:11988:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>repreſent, and thoſe graces alſo they had in meaſure, whereas in him they were in all ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, <hi>that ſo of his fulnes we might all receiue euen grace for grace:</hi> that is, aboundance of grace, and yet when he hath giuen vs all that wee haue, hee hauing neuer a whit the leſſe in himſelfe.</p>
            <p>And this very thing haue all the godly in all ages felt in themſelues, and confeſſed before others, that ſo if it were poſſible, they might be made partakers with them of the ſelfe ſame comfort. <hi>Abraham,</hi> ſaith Chriſt in the Goſpel after Iohn chap. 8. <hi>reioyced to ſee my day, and indeed ſaw it, and was glad.</hi> Chriſt meaning thereby that the aboundant riches of Gods grace that was in him, was made manifeſt in all former ages, the fathers by the eye of fayth (as the Apoſtle plainely ſheweth it Hebr. 11.) ſeeing in the promiſes that he ſhoulde come: of whome alſo as they did very ioyfully lay hold on by fayth ſo in reſpect of him and the ſweetnes of his promiſes they contemned all outward things. And Dauid no doubt of it in many places, fetteth out this grace and feeling to haue bin in himſelfe, and he to haue found fauour with the Lord, as in regard of comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table aſſurance of this matter. How gloriouſly in many places of the Goſpelles, doth Peter &amp; the reſt of the Apoſtles acknowledge it. In the 16. Chapter of this Goſpell, in the great va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rietie of opinions, that was amongſt men con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning
<pb facs="tcp:11988:18"/>Chriſt, ſome ſaying <hi>he was Elias, ſome Ieremias, or one of the Prophets.</hi> Peter in his owne name and in the name of the reſt, being demaunded what they thought, anſwered for them all, <hi>Thou art Chriſt the Sonne of the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing God:</hi> Which what was it elſe, but to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge that in him alone, and in none o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, was the fulneſſe of all goodneſſe, trueth, life, comfort or whatſoeuer elſe we can thinke of, or reckon vp? And in the ſixt of the Goſpel after Iohn, where it is ſhewed, that euen for ſome points of doctrine which our Sauiour Chriſt did deliuer but were not rightly vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, many of his diſciples went backe, and walked no more with him, Chriſt demaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of the twelue, whether they alſo woulde goe away, Peter anſwered (as he was alwayes a forward fellow) <hi>Maſter, to whom ſhall wee goe?</hi> as if hee ſhoulde ſay, certainly we cannot tell, <hi>Thou haſt the words of eternall life, and we beleeue and know that thou art that Chriſt that Sonne of the liuing God.</hi> But amongeſt all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers yea aboue the reſt as ſeemeth to me, the Apoſtle Paul is moſt plaine and plentifull in this poynt, whoſe ſeuerall ſentences recorded in his holy Epiſtles concerning this matter, would make almoſt a volume. But let vs take one or two in ſteede of all the reſt. In his firſt Epiſtle to the Corinthians, and firſt Chapter thereof towards the ende, he ſaith concerning Chriſt, and for the body of the faithfull, that
<pb facs="tcp:11988:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>he is made of God vnto vs, wiſdome, righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, ſanctification, and redemption,</hi> meaning thereby, that all, euen the chiefeſt graces that we can wiſh or would haue, as true and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly wiſedome, abſolute righteouſneſſe euen before God, houeſt and holy life in the ſight of men, and deliueraunce from all ſinne, and all miſeries and calamities whatſoeuer, are to be found onely in him and no where elſe. And in the Epiſtle to the Coloſſians, once or twice for fayling, he ſaith, that <hi>it pleaſed the Father that in him ſhould all fulnes dwell.</hi> chap. 1. And in the 2. chap. he ſaith, that <hi>in him dwelleth the fulnes of the Godhead bodily:</hi> meaning thereby that he was repleniſhed, not onely with moſt plentifull, but with infinite aboundance of all things, both diuine and humane, he being not onely moſt perfect in himſelfe, and paſſing all other things, but teaching his, that whoſoeuer hath him, neede require nothing more. Yea, that we might ſee in him, what wee our ſelues ſhould ſtriue vnto, euen euery one of vs, as in regard of our owne parte or feeling, hee doth not onely tell vs comfortable things, 1. Tim. 1. but ſetteth a worthy preface before it, ſaying, <hi>This is a true ſaying, and worthy by all meanes to be receiued, that Chriſt Ieſus came into the world to ſaue ſinners, of whom I am the chiefe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Neither neede wee to thinke this ſtrange, that godly men haue euery where acknowled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged it, for euen the diuelles and wicked men,
<pb facs="tcp:11988:19"/>conuicted with the euidence and cleareneſſe of this trueth, haue bin conſtrayned, though it haue bin full ſore againſt their willes, &amp; but for the further increaſe of their condemnation to confeſſe it, ſaying, <hi>What haue we to doe with thee, O Christ, the Sonne of the liuing God?</hi> And this is it alſo that S. Iames meaneth, when he ſayth of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, <hi>the deuilles beleeue &amp; tremble.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſurely God himſelfe doth not obſcure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, but moſt plainely rather propound this point, both in the giuing of his gracious pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes concerning Chriſt, and in the reiterating of them alſo, becauſe as the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>In Chriſt Ieſus all the promiſes of God are yea and Amen.</hi> As for example, when to our firſt pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents after the fall, hee ſayth, <hi>the ſeede of the woman ſhall breake or bruiſe the ſerpents head.</hi> And when to Abraham he ſayth, <hi>in thy ſeede ſhall all the nations of the earth be bleſſed.</hi> Which he doth repeat in Geneſis, twiſe or thriſe at the leaſt for ſayling: and the Apoſtle doth notably expound it in his Epiſtle to the Galathians, ſaying, <hi>in thy ſeed as of one, which one is Chriſt.</hi> That ſo in the particularizing of it wee might ſee ſtill this to be moſt true, that no where we can ſeeke for or find ſound con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation, but in him alone. Which alſo may yet further appeare by this, that God the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hath not onely prouided for the continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance and conueyance of this trueth, ouer or vnto men, by the audible voice of preaching
<pb facs="tcp:11988:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>in the publicke miniſtery of the Goſpell, tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching them to ſound and to publiſh it, ſaying, <hi>This is my welbeloued Sonne, in whom I am well pleaſed, heare him:</hi> but hath offered to ſeale it vp in the heartes and conſciences of them, by inſtituting &amp; ordayning certaine viſible ſignes and Sacraments, both in the law and vnder the goſpell, all leading vs not onely vnto Chriſt, but vnto all thoſe ſweete graces and heauenly comfortes that we receiue from him.</p>
            <p>To omit to ſpeake of the ſacraments of the olde teſtament, which yet notwithſtanding were for ſubſtance and matter, the ſame to the fathers that ours are to vs, and to come to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the newe Teſtament, yea and but to touch one of them onely, namely the Lords ſupper. What wonderfull and vnſpeakeable comfort, doth God in Chriſt offer vnto vs therein? To ſay nothing of thoſe that we receiue there, the pledges of his death, and bloud ſheading, and of all the graces that flow vnto vs therefrom, as forgiueneſſe of ſinnes, ſanctified vſe of the creatures, reconciliation to God, and ſundry ſuch like: what a maruailous mercy is this, that vnder thoſe elements of bread and wine, hee ſhould ſeale vp in our hearts not onely the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall ſtrength wee haue from him, to die the death of ſinne, and to liue the life of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, thorow his power, but alſo the heauenly comfort that he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municateth vnto vs: bread no more effectually or liuely ſtrengthning our
<pb facs="tcp:11988:20"/>hearts, nor wine more effectually making vs to be of cheerefull ſpirits, than Chriſt partaken of by fayth, filleth vs with all manner of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly and holy ioy.</p>
            <p>And by arguments taken from priuation if I may ſo ſay, wee may proue this point. The comfort that we ſpeake of is no where elſe to be ſound: therefore it muſt of neceſſitie be in him alone. If we would looke to Angels and ſaints departed out of this life, there is a double exception againſt them, for firſt we are vncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine of their good will and ſounde affection towards vs as in this behalfe: then we are ſure they cannot afford vs that we deſire, as who neither haue that power in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues, becauſe it properly &amp; onely belongeth vnto the Lord; and beſides are ſundred ſo farre from vs, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of diſtance of place, that they are not able to ſtretch out their ayd though they could helpe. As for the reſt of the creatures, they are as farre vnable and weake for this worke as the other, if not more. The diuelles and damned ſpirits will rather do what they can to torment vs, then yeeld any conſolation. Man and wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man that liue with vs in the world are infirme, and ſtand in neede as we our ſelues, and not able in the greatnes of their diſtreſſe, to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort themſelues, much leſſe vs: vnreaſonable creatures are tainted with our ſinnes, and ſith the wicked enioy them in greater portion than we, cannot yeelde conſolation. Our owne
<pb facs="tcp:11988:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>things that we haue in our owne power, as our wiues, our children, and friendes, either in hard heartedneſſe againſt vs, will become <hi>miſerable comforters</hi> vnto vs, as Iobs wife and friendes were, <hi>all the ſort of them,</hi> or elſe when we ſhal conſider what iniuries and indignities we haue offered them will increaſe our ſorrow. And the like may wee ſay of our health, wealth, ſtrength &amp;c. which beeing abuſed, will caſt downe rather then comfort.</p>
            <p>But whither am I carried in confirmation of this point? It is time as I take it, to make vſe of it, and ſo to proceed to the handling and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of ſome other doctrines.</p>
            <p>We may ſee by it as if it were in a cleare &amp; true looking glaſſe, the miſerable eſtate and wofull condition, of all in the worlde, that be without the knowledge and feeling of Chriſt, I ſay, both knowledge and feeling (and I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech you ioyne them both together, for they cannot be ſundred, no more then the ſoule and the body) becauſe as all without the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of him are vnder condemnation, ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny that know him, &amp; yet feele him not in faith and obedience, ſhall certainely periſh. For if that bee true which Chriſt himſelfe ſayth, Ioh. 17. <hi>This is life eternall to know thee to bee the onely true God and him whom thou hast ſent Ieſus Chriſt:</hi> then this by the contrary muſt needs be true alſo, that thoſe that knowe not God, and him whom he hath ſent Ieſus Chriſt,
<pb facs="tcp:11988:21"/>reſt vnder eternall condemnation, becauſe Chriſt ſayth, <hi>hee that beleeueth in the name of the onely begotten Sonne of God, ſhall not come into iudgement, but hath paſſed out of death in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to life:</hi> and againe, <hi>he that beleeueth not is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned already, becauſe he beleeueth not in the name of the onely Sonne of God.</hi> By which we ſee what ſentence to giue not only of the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then and gentiles, of whom the Apoſtle ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth Epheſ. 2. that <hi>they were without God in the world:</hi> neither yet of the Iewes, Turks &amp; others, who though they acknowledge God the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, yet obſtinately deny and refuſe the perſon of the ſonne: but alſo of many thouſandes of Chriſtians, whereof ſome as hereticks deny his natures, as the Anabaptiſtes, who deny his hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manitie, and our popiſh aduerſaries defacing his offices of Kingdome, in erecting and exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſing another gouernement, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he hath pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed of prieſthood, in placing their dayly vnbloody ſacrifice in ſtead of it: of prophecie, in bringing in new docirines, and eſtabliſhing traditions, and other ſuch traſh and trumpery. Other ſome againe knowing him, but denying him thorow looſe and lewd life, of whom we may ſay as the Apoſtle ſaith of ſome other not much vnlike them that <hi>When they knew the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer of godlines, they denied it notwithſtanding in their deeds:</hi> and of whom alſo we may ſay though it bee to their terror, as Chriſt ſayth Luk. 12. <hi>He that knoweth the will of his master,
<pb facs="tcp:11988:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>and doth it not, ſhall be beaten with many ſtripes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And yet let no man thinke this a hard or haſty iudgement, for heere wee ſpeake not the wordes of our owne heart or mouth, but of God, and may in ſome meaſure in this behalfe ſay, euen as Chriſt himſelfe ſayth Ioh. 12. <hi>I iudge no man, but there is one that iudgeth ſuch, euen the word that he hath ſpoken, it ſhall iudge them,</hi> according to which when we iudge, we cannot but iudge righteous iudgement, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it being all and onely trueth, it can giue no ſentence, ſaue according to the ſame. But to drawe it more neere to our preſent purpoſe and occaſion.</p>
            <p>We may learn from hence what is the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon why ſo many diſtreſſed ſpirits ly as it were broiling in the flame &amp; fire of a troubled and diſquieted he art. Sure he either they know not Chriſt, and the power of his grace and ſpirit, and then no maruell though they boyle and broile indeed, when they are touched with the ſting of conſcience for ſinne, and condemnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on therfore: For how can it be otherwiſe, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing there is neither forgiueneſſe of ſinnes, nor ouercomming of condemnation, nor any comfortable &amp; continuall feeling of any fauor but by him. Or els they feele him not with his force and effect that way, though they knowe their owne ſinne, the puniſhmentes due vnto them therefore, with the manifold vnworthy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes they find in themſelues, hindring them
<pb facs="tcp:11988:22"/>from comfort and conſolation. As for the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer ſort, I would wiſh them carefully &amp; pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully to labour the attainment of knowledge, becauſe then they are and ſhall bee a degree nearer to grace &amp; comfort than before, which hauing once obtained, and harty prayer made vnto God for the ſanctified vſe, continuance and increaſe therof in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, they ſhall no doubt in good time come to feeling: but till then let them neuer thinke of it, for all their thoughtes that way ſhall bee but loſt labour, becauſe not knowing, they ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not beleeue, for how can any man be perſwaded of the thinges he knoweth not? And for the other I would in the feare of God counſell them, neuer to thinke of ſinne alone, or of condemnation by it ſelf, or of their owne vnworthineſſe apart, for then certainely they ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not chooſe, but be much diſcomforted &amp; greatly caſt down, but to ioyn alwayes ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with the remedies that God hath prouided &amp; giuen them there againſt, as oppoſing againſt ſinne, Chriſts ſuffrings, and the merits thereof, which being ſtrong to take away the cauſe, cannot but vtterly remooue the effect, that is, condemnation: and to oppoſe againſt their owne vnworthineſſe, the worthines of him that hath deſerued all in all, not for himſelfe, for he needed no merites, as neuer hauing offended; but for vs, that in his righteouſnes wee might ſtand pure and cleane in the ſight of God. And then no doubt but if we doe this, theſe tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions
<pb facs="tcp:11988:22" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſhall be the more eaſie, and the ſooner o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uercome, ſpecially if we adioyne therewith all praier for the increaſe &amp; ſtrengthening of our faith, to apply vnto our ſelues all the ſweete promiſes and comfortable examples of the word, which indeed, be not only as manie ſure ſeales and pledges ſet thereunto, but ſo many particular documentes to inſtruct vs what to doe, becauſe God is not in this ſort or ſenſe, a general God to all, but a particular God to the faithful, &amp; a ſpecial God to euery one of them, as may appeare by theſe words of the faithfull, <hi>I thanke my God,</hi> and in prayer, <hi>My God, my God, &amp;c.</hi> And yet this applying of him vnto our ſelues doth not ſtraighten Gods goodnes in it ſelfe, for that is infinitely large, nor hinder it from others, for he may and doeth giue to all aboundantly, and yet all they haue to the full, and he himſelfe neuer a whit the leſſe therfore.</p>
            <p>A ſecond doctrine that we may learne from hence is this, that the eſtate of a diſtreſſed and an afflicted ſpirite, is not ſo hard or heauy, ſo dangerous deadly or deſperate, as many men in the world take it, and would make it to bee. This is gathered from hence, yea and confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med alſo by this, that he doth heer ſo comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tablie call vpon them, and commaund them to come vnto him, which if they had been paſt hope he would not haue done, for our Sauiour hath not done or ſaid any thing in vaine. Surely nothing was hidden from him, hee knew their eſtate, and accordingly framed himſelfe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to.
<pb facs="tcp:11988:23"/>And indeede to ſay true, it had been to no purpoſe, becauſe being paſt hope, it ſhuld haue been in vain, either to haue called or comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. But Chriſt ſheweth rather the quite and cleane contrarie, namely, that it is good and comfortable, as we may perceiue by this, that our Sauiour Chriſt ſo tenderly regardeth them that be plunged into that miſery.</p>
            <p>And this we may vnderſtand alſo by many reaſons as well as by that before alleaged. All things in the world, and therefore this, muſt of neceſſity come from God or from nature. That which is from God, is as himſelf good yea, very good: that which is from nature, is as nature, vitiated and corrupted. But this indeed is no naturall thing, as may appeare by this, that na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture in the corruptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of it rather ſootheth men in ſin, than any maner of way chargeth them withall: yea nature is ſo farre from working it, that it rather ſhunneth it, and flyeth from it as a moſt grieuous euill. And beſides, if it were na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall and from man, why ſhould not all be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſed with it, ſeeing all men are meerlie na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall, and haue alike ſinned as in regard of the taint of original ſin? and though it may be that actually all men haue not ſinned alike, yet ſith euery man in his meaſure or maner, hath bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken the law of God: if it were from nature it would follow thereupon that euery man ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther more or leſſe ſhuld be touched therwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, becauſe euery man hath more or leſſe ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. It being therefore from God, as may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare
<pb facs="tcp:11988:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>by this alſo, that he hath ordayned many meanes, and amongſt the reſt the execution of iudgme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, and the denouncing of the ſame, by the miniſtery of the law, and his vſing of the ſame, as a worthy inſtrume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, to bring men ther unto; it will follow thereupon that it cannot be but good, becauſe nothing commeth from him who is all ſoueraigne goodnes in himſelfe, but that which is good euen as he himſelfe is. And if it be good, as it muſt needs bee co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming from him, then it is not euill, or ſo dangerous, dead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie and deſperate as many men make it.</p>
            <p>Beſides, let vs but a little regard the perſons, who are moſt touched therwith, &amp; we ſhal ſee that they be the deareſt &amp; neereſt vnto God, &amp; are beſt beloued of him. Amongſt the Fathers vnder the law, were any more excellent than Abraham, than Moſes, than Dauid, than Iſaiah? Of Abraham it is recorded, that <hi>hee was the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the faithful, &amp; the friend of God.</hi> Of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes it is affirmed, that <hi>hee was the faithfulleſt in the houſe of God, as a ſeruant.</hi> Of Dauid, that <hi>hee was a man euen according to the heart of God.</hi> And yet howe much were euerie one of theſe humbled? Let Dauid ſtand vs in ſteed of al. How many not only here and there ſentences or ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes thorowout his booke of Pſalmes, but whole Pſalmes of this ſubiect and matter, plainly ſhew him, to haue bin far throwne down and hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bled? To reckon them all would require much time, and therefore to rehearſe them in whole or in part much more: but let him that doubteth of
<pb facs="tcp:11988:24"/>the trueth of this read Pſal 6.13.38.77.102. &amp; 130. and if by them he will not bee perſwaded, that Dauid was touched to the quick this way, no thing I ſuppoſe will cauſe him to beleeue it. Vnder the Goſpell we haue our ſauiour Chriſt himſelf, the principall preacher or miniſter ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, a plaine patterne of this point. His whole life was lead vnder this eſtate, yea and as wee may ſay, laide downe in it alſo, as it is at long and at large deſcribed vnto vs by the Euangeliſts. And this argument alſo, I meane concerning the hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliation of our Sauiour, euery way the Apoſtle in his Epiſtle to the Hebrewes, doth not onely handle in the ſixe or ſeuen firſt chapters of that his epiſtle, but teacheth Gods people to make ſpeciall vſe thereof for inſtruction and comfort. And if anie will imagine that he was ſo throwne downe, becauſe hee was beſt, yea onely able to raiſe vp himſelfe and others alſo: let vs turne our eyes from him vnto others, and yet we ſhall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the ſame ſtill. The Apoſtle Paule was an <hi>elected veſſell, &amp; choſen to cary Chriſtes name a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst the Gentiles:</hi> and yet his ſtate and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition this way is notably deſcribed in many places of his ſeconde Epiſtle to the Corinthians, but ſpecially in the fourth chapter, where hee ſaith: <hi>We are afflicted on euery ſide, yet are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> not in d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſtreſſe: we are in doubt, but yet wee deſpaire not: we are perſecuted, but not forſaken: caſt down, but we periſh not.</hi> And he maketh a particular re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cit all of many of them in the eleuenth chapter following. But ſpecially that of the twelfth ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth
<pb facs="tcp:11988:24" rendition="simple:additions"/>for this purpoſe, where hee ſaith, <hi>Leaſt I ſhould be exalted out of meaſure, through the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance or excellency</hi> (for the Greek word doth ſignifie both the one and the other) <hi>of reuelati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, there was giuen vnto me a pricke in the fleſh, the meſſenger Sathan to buffet me: for this thing I beſought the Lorde thriſe that it might depart from me, but he ſaid vnto me, my grace is ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent for thee, for my power is made perfect thorowe weaknes.</hi> And ſhall we thinke that God woulde lay any thing vpon theſe the only worthies of the world, ſaue that which was good indeed? If we imagine ſo we are much deceiued. And thinke that that will neither agree with Gods nature in loue, nor ſtand with the fauour &amp; affection that he beareth vnto his children. For no doubt but as he loued them moſt dearlie, ſo he beſtowed vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them the greateſt and beſt bleſſings.</p>
            <p>Again if in al affliction we may in our meaſure ſay as Dauid the Prophet ſaid, in ſome particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars of his owne. <hi>It is good for me, O Lord, that I haue been troubled, for before I was afflicted I went astray, but now I haue learned to keepe thy law.</hi> Then much more in afflictions of this kind, I meane ſorrow and ſicknes of ſoule for ſin paſt, God vſing it not only as a meane to draw vs to repentance for that which is paſt, but to make vs in time hereafter to come, more wary of and watchfull ouer that, that in former time hath bitten vs and pinched vs by the heart, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoking vs in the heauines of our ſpirites to ſpend time that way, to prouide comfort for ourſelues,
<pb facs="tcp:11988:25"/>ſpirituall I meane, that others are conſtrayned to imploy about bodily eaſe, releefe and pleaſure. And ſurely the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theſe inward ſorrowes &amp; griefs, cannot chooſe but be good, not onlie becauſe they are occupied about a more excellent part, the ſoule, I meane, which God no doubt doth eſpecially regarde, but alſo becauſe they bring forth better, at leaſt ſure I am more ſpirituall ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectes: as becauſe they pinch more, more ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt prayer for grace to beare with patience, to vndergo with profit, and to ouercome through ſtrength, and doe more conforme vs vnto the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage of our head in his ſuſtringes (who indured much more this way, than any other way) and therfore alſo better or more excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. Where we muſt yet further note, that that is not ſimply or only, as in regarde of the afflictions themſelues, but becauſe God accompanieth them with the power of his ſanctifying ſpirit, which maketh vs in ſome meaſure, not only <hi>peatakers of the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine nature, whileſt wee fly the corruptions that are in the world,</hi> but like vnto God, as in other reſpectes, ſo in this, that as he cauſeth the <hi>rage of men to turne vnto his praiſe,</hi> and at the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing yea and euer ſince to, <hi>commandeth light to ſhine out of darknes:</hi> ſo we out of the folly of our own ſins learne ſpirituall wiſedom, &amp; from their darknes which is more palpable and groſſe than that of Egypt, labour and learne to ſetch the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall light of a holy life.</p>
            <p>And a further proof yet we haue of this point, in that God himſelfe is pleaſed well to like of &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:11988:25" rendition="simple:additions"/>highly to commende this eſtate and condition: We know and beleeue that he alone is the beſt able to diſcerne of men and matters: and we are throughly perſwaded of this alſo, that for his entire vprightneſſe, he cannot giue wrong ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence or iudgment. For howſoeuer men thorow blindnes, partialitie or other corrupted reſpects haue been and are fouly miſled, &amp; erred in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of opinion and fact, yet none of theſe thinges falling into God, he can do no otherwiſe but de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine according to right, ſo abſolute and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect is all and euery thing that is in God. But hee hath told vs, that he liketh wel of, &amp; will reſpect and regard indeed thoſe that are this way exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed. Of which if any man doubt, let him but marke and imbrace that which we ſpeak accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding vnto godlines and trueth, and I doubt not but he ſhall be well perſwaded. In the 51. Pſal. Dauid as well experienced in theſe caſes as any man, ſaith thus: <hi>The ſacrifices of God</hi> (that is to ſay, ſuch as the Lord now delighteth in and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepteth of) <hi>are a broken ſpirit:</hi> by which he mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth a mind that is bruiſed and caſt downe in it ſelfe with the priuity of his owne infirmity and vnworthineſſe. What can be more plain? what can be more pregnant? And yet as though this were not ſufficient, he addeth further, <hi>A broken and a contrite heart, O God, thou wilt not deſpiſe.</hi> Gods not deſpiſing is indeed eſteeming, and he vſeth ſo meane a ſpeech, the better to expreſſe ſo excellent a matter, for no doubt of it, but he wil well accept thereof, as his owne work in vs. And
<pb facs="tcp:11988:26"/>agreeable vnto this is that of the Prophet Iſaiah in the 66. chap. <hi>I looke to him</hi> (ſaith God) <hi>that is poore and broken in ſpirit, and that tremble that my word.</hi> As if he ſhould ſay, others I regard not though they come with their hands full of ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices: for that hypocrites may and do performe, but this none can come vnto indeed, but ſuch as be ſound hearted, and aſſuredly belong vnto me, and are indeed my holy temple and dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling place. And what ſhall wee ſay of that, that Salomon ſpeaketh euen from God himſelfe in the 28. chap. of the Prouerbs. <hi>Bleſſed is the man that feareth much continually.</hi> Is it not a plaine proofe of this point? And doth it not directlie croſſe our corrupted iudgment? Wee ſay they are in miſerable and wretched eſtate. But wee are ignorant and cannot diſcerne of thoſe mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters ſpecially, no more than a blind man is able to iudge of colours. But God ſaith he or they be bleſſed. If he be the <hi>only wiſe God,</hi> why ſtay wee not our ſelues vpon his ſentence?</p>
            <p>To ſhut vp, and that as if it were in a word or two the confirmation of this point, wee ſay that whoſoeuer either conſidereth God from whom theſe anguiſhes and diſtreſſes, are ſent to good ends doubtleſſe, as in regard of his people; or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gardeth the perſons vpon whom they are laide, to wit the deareſt and the beſt of Gods people; or reſpecteth the fruites and effectes that they bring forth in the ſeruants of God; or beleeueth God ſo highly accouning of them, hee cannot chooſe but giue glorie to God, &amp; acknowledge
<pb facs="tcp:11988:26" rendition="simple:additions"/>the trueth of this, namely that the ſtate and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of a man or woman wounded in ſpirit, is not ſo hard or heauy, ſo dangerous or deadlie, as many times we take it, or men make it to be.</p>
            <p>But now let vs deſcende to the vſes of it. By all this wee may ſee howe much they are out of the way that iudge the diſquiet and diſtreſſed e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate of Gods people in this worlde, either by God to bee layde vpon them for ſinne, which is falſe, for God doth not alwayes puniſh his for their iniquities, and there are many cauſes that may mooue the godly to mourne, as well as for their owne ſinnes, for examples, the miſchiefes intended and practiſed againſt the Church, the diſorders and breaches of the common wealth, the generall ouerflowing of ſinne and iniquitie in others with ſundry ſuch like: or els take it to be meer madnes in them, or at leaſt ſuperfluitie and predominance, and ouerruling of melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cholie. As for madneſſe ſurely, call it by what name you wil, frenſie, lunacie, or I cannot tell what, it cannot be ſo, for then it ſhould goe and come, according to the increaſe and waning of the Moone, and ſhould cauſe them affected therewith to be ſo vnorderly, yea ſo vnruly, as no man or matter almoſt ſhould be able to holde or guide them. But thoſe that are in this way touched, we know to bee for the moſt part in one eſtate, and ſo farre from vnrulines, that they are very meeke, patient, and ready to be guided, hauing ſo profited vnder the hand of God, and by the feeling of their owne vnworthineſſe, that
<pb facs="tcp:11988:27"/>if any come to them, and handle them roughly in word or deed, they beare it with quietneſſe, and ſay in ſome meaſure as the faithfull doe in the Prophet Micah. <hi>J will beare the wrath of the Lord, becauſe I haue ſinned againſt him, vntill he plead my cauſe, and execute iudgment for me: at which time hee will bring mee foorth to the light, &amp; I ſhal ſee his righteouſnes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And as for melancholy, I will not deny in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede, but that the conflict of conſcience may be ſomewhat increaſed by abundance of that perillous humor? And I thinke no man that knoweth what it meaneth, and the conceits it worketh in them, in whom it aboundeth, will euer gaineſay it. But there is not all. For if it were onely from thence, why ſhoulde not all melancholike perſons haue it in proportion ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the ſuperaboundance of that hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor in them? But that is not ſo, as dayly expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience ſheweth. Or why ſhould others, and of other complexions alſo, beſides the melancho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licke, be ſicke of this diſeaſe? and that many times more dangerouſly then diuers of thoſe that haue aboundance of melancholy bearing ſway in them. Surely God ſheweth vs hereby, not onely that their iudgement is corrupt that thus thinke, but alſo that they are blinde, and buzze out a word touching a matter that they haue ſmall skill in and leſſe experience of, yea none at all. Small skill, becauſe they <hi>knowe not the Scriptures, nor the power of God,</hi> without which indeede no man ſhall bee skilfully ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted
<pb facs="tcp:11988:27" rendition="simple:additions"/>with theſe cauſes. No experience, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they neuer felte hell in their heartes, or Gods wrath againſt men for ſinne, vnleſſe it haue bin in them, either as a flaſh of lightning for a while, to make them without excuſe, or as a mighty fire and flame to torment them with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out eaſe, that ſo they and the wicked that deny God, heauen, hell, immortalitie of ſoule and all, might ſee in themſelues, though they haue no comfort thereby, but wonderfull terror ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, how much they are ſeduced. We ſay and we ſay truely, that a blind man ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not diſcerne of colours. And why ſo? becauſe he that muſt iudge thereof, muſt both haue ſight and wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. One of theſe the blinde man lacketh if not both. Yea we ſee many that notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding they haue their eyes, are not yet able (for want of iudgement &amp; experience) to diſcerne of the diuerſitie of colours, ſpecially if ſo be they be mingled or compounded. Hee that muſt determine rightly of this matter, either as in regard of himſelfe, or as in reſpect of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther men, muſt haue more then the eyes of his head, and more then the vnderſtanding of his naturall heart, <hi>for the naturall man perceiueth not the things that belong to the ſpirit of God, neither indeed can he, becauſe they are spiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally diſcerned, and he is carnall and ſold vnder ſinne.</hi> Yea he muſt haue euen the eies of God, and wiſedome &amp; vnderſtanding from aboue, that is ſpirituall, and ſuch as he vouchſaueth to beſtow onely vpon his owne children, and to
<pb facs="tcp:11988:28"/>which alſo, for their better incouragement of them in it, of his owne mercy he promiſeth a bleſſing in the 41. Pſalme, ſaying, <hi>Bleſſed is he that iudgeth wiſely of the poore, the Lord ſhall deliuer him in the time of trouble. The Lord wil keepe him and preſerue him aliue: hee ſhall bee bleſſed vpon the earth, and thou wilt not deliuer him vnto the will of his enemies. The Lord wil ſtrengthen him vpon the bed of ſorrow, thou haſt turned all his bed in his ſicknes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherefore when the afflicted perſon hath many times his griefes inlarged within him, not onely by the ſight and ſenſe of his owne ſinne, and Gods wrath againſt the ſame, but by this alſo, that ſuch a man and ſuch a man thinketh ſo of him, and ſayth ſo of him, wee may ſee hee hath in a readines, and may eaſily anſwere euen for himſelfe in this behalfe with the Apoſtle, or as the Apoſtle did in another not much vnlike ſaying. <hi>It is a ſmall matter for me to be iudged of man or of mans daies:</hi> &amp; the rather too, becauſe God hath not giuen iudgement vnto men, but reſerued it in his owne handes, as who is beſt able euery way moſt rightly to pronounce. Agayne hee may well and truely ſay thus to his owne ſoule, they that ſo cenſure me, are ignorant, or vnexperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enced, or hard hearted, or partiall, and one way or another ſouly ouertaken and vnfitte to giue ſentence: they know not themſelues or their owne eſtate, howe ſhoulde they knowe mine. We muſt ſtand or fall to the Lord, and
<pb facs="tcp:11988:28" rendition="simple:additions"/>not vnto men. With theſe &amp; ſuch like are they to rayſe vp their heartes, and cheare their ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits againſt the blind, vnexperienced, raſh, yea vncharitable iudgement of other men, hudled out thicke and threefold againſt them, in the dayes of their affliction and ſorrow. And if in other caſes of farre lighter waight, the Apoſtle wil not haue vs to <hi>iudge one another,</hi> but ſharp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly reproueth it, ſaying, <hi>What art thou that iudgest another mans ſeruant? He ſtandeth or falleth to his owne Lord, yea he ſhall be establi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, for God is able to make him ſtand.</hi> Shall we thinke hee woulde approue or beare, ſo groſſe a corruption and foule a fault as this? No verely. Let vs learne therefore, to lay our hands eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vpon our hearts &amp; our mouths both, &amp; not giue our ſelues libertie either to thinke euill of, or to ſpeake hardly of, thoſe that bee thus throwne downe, and humbled vnder Gods mighty hand, for that is preſumptuous againſt the Lord, and vncharitable towards men.</p>
            <p>And another vſe may be made of this point as in regard of the faithfull themſelues, who minding too much their owne ſinnes, and by meanes there of miſerie and vnworthineſſe in themſelues, &amp; iudgements from God againſt them for the ſame, many times make their owne mouthes meanes to expreſſe fearefull thinges againſt their owne ſoules: as for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, no man in ſo wofull taking as I, I feare I am a caſtaway, or els why ſhould I thus bee tormented? And theſe thinges I doubt not but
<pb facs="tcp:11988:29"/>they deliuer from a heart, that feeleth as much as the mouth expreſſeth. Howbeit I ſay, what art thou, that takeſt the Lords office into thy hands? and deliuereſt theſe hard and heauie things, and that not againſt other men (which were indeed vncharitable) but euen thine own ſelfe which is vnnaturall? Tell me I pray thee. May blindnes ſo farre preiudice mens iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, that it ſhall hinder them from behol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding their owne and other mens ſtates? and ſhall it not obſcure thine owne alſo? yea, and that euen concerning thy ſelfe, and touching thine owne preſent ſtate? But further knowe this, O man, that ſometimes greatnes and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance of griefes, maketh the beſt of Gods Saintes to ſay as much againſt themſelues as thou doeſt, and yet for all that bee in neuer a whit the worſe caſe. Dauid in the xxii. Pſa. cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth out, <hi>My God, my God, why haſt thou forſake<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> me?</hi> And yet euen the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he was neare vnto God, yea &amp; deare vnto him alſo, or els he coulde not haue called vpon God, and that in ſuch parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular maner, applying him to himſelfe as hee did, neither would the Lord haue ſo graciouſly graunted him his requeſtes. And why ſhould not this be thy ſtate, rather than the ſtate of a damned or reprobated wretch? To vphold thy heart, thou haſt ſomething, euen the ſanctified examples of the people of God, but to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe thee ſo aboue meaſure, thou haſt no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but imagination and conceit, either of that which is not in God, or if it bee, is not in
<pb facs="tcp:11988:29" rendition="simple:additions"/>him to that ende that thou ſuppoſeſt: or els of that which is not in thy ſelfe; or if it be, is not in that meaſure and quantitie, or to thoſe ends that thou imagineſt.</p>
            <p>Beſides I beſeech you conſider, that it is one thing what men ſpeake of themſelues, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their preſent feeling, either of ſinne in their ſoules, or the wrath of God againſt them therefore, which many times may be more tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is eyther meete or true: &amp; another what God is in his owne nature, &amp; what he himſelfe ſaith of them. God is exceedingly good &amp; merciful, and is not indeede bound to ratifie euery ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of mans mind or mouth, which he vtte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth either againſt his owne ſoule, or againſt o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. I hope no man is, ſure I am no man can be rightly perſwaded, that any particular per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is more than the whole Church. And yet God no otherwiſe approoueth the Churches iudgement to ratifie it in heauen, than they on the earth bind according to his will. And why ſhould it be otherwiſe as in regard of particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar perſons? Haue they better priuiledges than the whole Church hath: if it bee ſo, let them produce a lawe, not of the twelue tables a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the Romans, but of the ten comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dementes amongſt the people of God, or elſe there is no credit to be giuen. O my brethren, it fareth in the diſeaſes of the minde, as it doth in the ſicknes of the body. Many a man, yea skilfull Phyſitions, take them to be at deathes doore, when God giueth afterwards long life.
<pb facs="tcp:11988:30"/>On the other ſide ſome bleſſe themſelues in their owne heartes and thinke all is well, when death ſodainely ſeizeth vpon them, &amp; leadeth them to the graue and hell. Remember I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech you what was ſaid before out of the 28. of the Prouerbs, <hi>Bleſſed is the man</hi> (ſayth the Lorde there) <hi>that feareth much continually.</hi> This ſtate and condition of ours, whenſoeuer or whereſoeuer it pleaſeth God to exerciſe vs therewithall, is a principall argument vnto vs, that God woulde not haue vs <hi>periſh with this wicked world,</hi> hee by this as by other meanes thorow his grace, making vs able thus to iudge our ſelues. And indeede to haue ſuch a feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and checking heart of our ſelues, for ſinne paſt, or for feare to fall into it hereafter, is one plaine difference betwixt the godly and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly, who are ſeldome or neuer this way tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, at the leaſt with comfortable effect. And therefore let the afflicted ſoule, gather conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation to his conſcience, and correct his iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: for ſurely that which he taketh to be bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter as gall or wormewood, is by the Lord him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, and not by the voyce of man to be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claymed to bee ſweete as hony, or the hony combe.</p>
            <p>The promiſe ſpecified in the laſt wordes of this verſe, commeth nowe to bee looked into. Out of which gracious and ſweet promiſe we may learne two things. One, that the fulnes of all ſpirituall ioy and comfort is to be found in Ieſus Chriſt and no where elſe: which becauſe
<pb facs="tcp:11988:30" rendition="simple:additions"/>it is the ſame that hath bin handled hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, wee will but onely touch, and put you in mind of it, not ſtanding vpon it, becauſe it is done already. And indeede though the point be excellent, and would be handled againe &amp; againe, yet becauſe the time paſſeth away, &amp; we are to come to other points, we will ſay no more. Onely let the faithfull conſcience looke well vnto it, and prouide his comfort this way, or elſe let him know he ſhall neuer be comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted indeede.</p>
            <p>The other is this, that if a man will find ſound co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort indeede, he muſt be wel acquainted with the promiſes of the word. This doctrin as others is both gathered out of this place, &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>firmed by it, as may appeare by this that our Sauior Chriſt is here ſo plentiful in the promiſes, <hi>I will refreſh you, yee ſhall finde reſt vnto your ſoules:</hi> which courſe alſo he obſerueth in many other places: <hi>I wil haue mercy and not ſacrifice:</hi> and againe, <hi>I came not to call the righteous, but ſinners to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance.</hi> And moſt ſweete is that in the third chapt. of the Goſpell according to S. Iohn, <hi>God ſo loued the world, that he hath giuen his only be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten ſonne, that whoſoeuer beleeueth in him ſhould not periſh, but haue euerlaſting life.</hi> Ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is this his practiſe onlie, but the ſpirit alſo in all the writings of the old and new Teſtament is large this way, and ſpeciallie in that euangeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call prophet Iſaiah, as we may ſee by the mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold promiſes contayned therein, and ſpeciallie in three or foure chapters together, as 53.54.55.
<pb facs="tcp:11988:31"/>&amp;c. But amongſt the reſt how comfortable is that of chapt. 41. from whence euen vnto the end of his prophecie almoſt, hee doth nothing els but publiſh promiſes and confolations: a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt which howſoeuer hee doe ſometimes intermingle terrour and threatning, yet he doth it to no other onde, but to make the mercies of God, more exceedingly merciful: as ſometimes to diſgrace a baſe colour, or to make a colour that is perfect indeed, to appeare more beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and orient, wee ſet by it another that is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſo glorious and good. But to our purpoſe, I ſay, howe comfortable is that of <hi>Iſaiah.</hi> 41. where the Lord commaundeth his miniſters to <hi>comfort, yea to comfort his people, and to ſeeke out for them, and to ſpeake</hi> ſuch things vnto them, as may delight and affect their heattes, and to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clame vnto them that the <hi>ſet time is accompli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, that their iniquitie is pardoned, and that they haue receiued double at the Lords hands for all their ſinne.</hi> And this is yet further made plain by this, that though al the word generally be the obiect of our faith, teaching vs indeed what wee ſhould beleeue and do for Gods glory heer, and our endleſſe glorification els where; yet the principal props and ſtayes of our conſciences, for comfort &amp; conſolation indeed, are no where els to befound, but in the gracious and ſweet promiſes contayned therein: which alſo is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt euen by the very practiſe of God himſelfe euery where propounding them to an afflicted and diſtreſſed heart, as the principall and pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar
<pb facs="tcp:11988:31" rendition="simple:additions"/>remedie againſt the ſicknes of our ſoules that way. In the 103. Pſalme he ſaith, that look <hi>how much more high the heauens are ouer the the earth, ſo much doth his goodnes preuaile vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them that feare him.</hi> Againe, <hi>he remooueth our ſinnes as farre fromvs, as the Eaſt is from the Weſt.</hi> By two fit ſimilitudes taken fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> things that are ſubiect to our fight amplifying the grace and mercie of God, &amp; oppoſing the ſame againſt our tranſgreſſions. And in Iſaiah 1. he ſaith thus, <hi>Though your ſi nes were as skarlet, they ſhall be as ſnow, and though they were as cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſin, yet they ſhall be whiter than wooll.</hi> And fearing leaſt men woulde not willinglie come, how doth he there intereat vs? ſaying, <hi>Come now I pray you and let vs reaſon the cauſ together,</hi> as though he ſhould ſay, let vs friendly conferre of the matter. If you will but lend and bend your care, and be touched with the true ſenſe of my righteouſnes and your owne ſinnes, I promiſe faithfully, that I will for mine own mercies ſake put away all your tranſgreſſions whatſoeuer, though they be neuer ſo great or grieuous. That ſhall not let my worke in you: my mercy ſhall ſurmount all: yea your miſery (if you ſoundlie turne) ſhall magnifie the greatnes of the abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant riches of my mercy. The newe couenant that God maketh with his people in the 31. chap. of Ieremie, (and to the end that we might know it indeed to be a promiſe of the new teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, it is repeated by the Apoſtle Heb. 8.) how comfortable and full of ſweet promiſes is that?
<pb facs="tcp:11988:32"/>
               <hi>After thoſe dayes ſaith the Lord, I will put my law in their inwarde partes, and write it in their heartes, and I will be their God and they ſhall bee my people: and they ſhall teach no more euery man his neighbour, and euery man his brother, ſaying: know the Lord for they ſhall all know me from the leaſt of them vnto the greateſt; ſaith the Lord, for J will forgiue their iniquity, and will remember their ſinnes no more.</hi> And if the olde teſtament be ſo plentifull, what ſhall we thinke of the new, which doth as of purpoſe propound, and handle this point or queſtion? Chriſt himſelf ſaith, Mat. 7. <hi>Aske, and it ſhall be giuen vnto you, ſeeke and ye ſhall find, knock and it ſhall be opened vnto you.</hi> And in the 7. of Iohn, in the laſt and great day of the feaſt, he ſtood &amp; crying out ſaid, <hi>He that beleeueth in mee, as ſaith the ſcripture, out of his belly ſhall flow riuers of water of life:</hi> and in the 12. of that Goſpell, <hi>He that beleeueth in me, yea though he were dead, yet ſhall he liue: and whoſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer liueth and beleeueth in me ſhall neuer die.</hi> Is not that of the ſame nature which hee ſpeaketh of in another Euangeliſſt? <hi>The whole need not the Phyſition, but they that are ſicke. I am not come to call the righteous, but the ſinners to repentance.</hi> And what may we think of that which is allea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged in the 12. of the Goſpell after Mathewe, out of the prophet Iſaiah, <hi>A bruiſed reed ſhall he not breake, and ſmoking flaxe ſhal he not quench, till he bring foorth iudgement vnto victory?</hi> Out of Paules epiſtles wee haue ſpoken ſomewhat be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in the firſt point of doctrine that was gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
<pb facs="tcp:11988:32" rendition="simple:additions"/>out of this text, yet take one or two. In the 2. to the Corinth. chap. 6. he ſaith, <hi>We are the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of the liuing God, as God hath ſaid I will dwel amongst them and walk there, and I will be their God, and they ſhal be my people. Yea I will be a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vnto you, and ye ſhall bee my ſons and daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters ſaith the Lorde almighty.</hi> And the ſame A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle deliuereth a notable promiſe, with a glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious &amp; comfortable preface, prefixed before it alſo. 1. Tim. 1. <hi>This is a true ſaying and worthy to be receined of all men, that Chriſt Ieſus came into the world to ſaue ſinners, of whom I am the chief.</hi> May we not of theſe and thouſandes ſuch like, ſay as the Apoſtle Peter doth, that <hi>moſt great &amp; precious promiſes are giuen vnto vs,</hi> &amp; that euen for that end which he expreſſeth there, namely, that <hi>by them wee ſhoulde bee partakers of the diuine nature, whilest we fly the corruption that is in the world thorow luſt?</hi> Are not theſe great promiſes, and may iuſtly bee ſo called, becauſe they proceed from the great God, &amp; propounde vnto vs great and excellent matters? May wee not eſteeme them precious, not only for the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie and excellencie of them, but alſo becauſe they vnderprop our precious faith? Are wee not made in a double reſpect by them <hi>partakers of the diuine nature?</hi> 1. that as in regard God is ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and chearefull, we are alſo become comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table, and repleniſhed with ſpiritual ioy. 2. That as be ceaſeth from ſin, and is continually occu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pied in well doing, ſo we learne thereby in our meaſure and maner to <hi>die the death of ſinne, and
<pb facs="tcp:11988:33"/>to liue the l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fe of righteouſnes:</hi> What other men may think I know not, but to me it ſeemeth that God thus in his worde, ſetting promiſes againſt ſin, mindeth nothing els but to ſhew that as ſin is it that moſt ſtingeth the conſcience, ſo the meane to heale that byting (as if it were the bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen Serpent ſet vp to cure the bytinges of fierie Serpents) &amp; to bring comfort againſt the ſame, is the promiſes of God propounded vnto vs in the word, and ſelt in our hearts by faith.</p>
            <p>And this is ſo plaine and euident a truth, that euen there where God ſeemeth moſt to terrifie, I meane in denouncing the threats of his law, or iudgments againſt ſinne, he yet thinketh vpon, not only his mercy in himſelfe, but as it is mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted vnto men, he euen there, either plainly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing promiſes of bleſſing, grace, and fauor, or els cloſely implying &amp; vnderſtanding them. Wherein ſurely he dealeth no otherwiſe, then he doth in the commandements, by a good thing commanded, forbidding the contrary cuill, and by an euil thing prohibited, inioyning ſtraightly the louing and doing of the contrary good, that ſo wee ſeeing what God aymeth at both in his precepts promiſes, threates, and all namely not only our obedience and humiliation, but com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort alſo, we might learne to attaine that, and to look to and for that, which he hath prouided for our good.</p>
            <p>And yet we ſhall more clearlie perceiue and behold this trueth, if we reſpect Gods worde, or the holy ſcirptures in the ſeuerall partes thereof,
<pb facs="tcp:11988:33" rendition="simple:additions"/>fundred as if it were from the promiſes. For if we looke vpon the threats contained therin againſt ſinne and ſinners, they will be ſo farre off from performing this dutie of comfort and conſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that they will rather worke in vs horror and trembling, and make vs to bee ſo not only caſt downe, but diſmayed in ourſelues, as wee ſhall hardly, or not at al admit comfort. The doctrine of the law ſeparated from the curſe and threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning due to the tranſgreſſors thereof, will indeed ſet before vs Gods abſolute and exact righteou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and diſconer vnto vs the duties, that wee ſhuld do to him and to our neighbors. But when we conſider withall that it ſetteth out our ſinne againſt euery particular precept, that will bee ſo farre from yeelding vs conſololation, that it will ouer whelme vs with deſpaire, when wee either reſpect Gods abſolure righteouſnes, or our own innumerable tranſgreſſions againſt his bleſſed law. And though I doubt not but theſe former things may bee good and powerfull to humble vs and ſomake vs indeed more fit for conſolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and comfort, euen as preparatiues going be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore better phyſicke, for the ſcouring away of bodily diſeaſes, yet can they not of themſelues helpe or heale (but wounde and terrifie rather) for that is the peculiar both office and worke of Gods promiſes made eſſectuall in our heartes by the touch and operation of the ſpirit. Nay, I will ſay more than that, though the ground of Chriſtian religion, and the maine points of faith be excellent things, and haue their vſe not only
<pb facs="tcp:11988:34"/>for increaſe of knowledge, but euen for the buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of vs vp in care and conſcience of well do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and being wel felt may anſwer many temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations that ariſe in a ſcrupulous and doubtfull mind: yet ſtill the promiſes of the worde, mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter matter of aſſured comfort and comforta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble aſſurance and feeling: which alſo wee may perceiue by this, that many may haue the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of faith, and yet in the daye of temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, not be able to ſtrengthen their owne hands or others.</p>
            <p>But to proceede a little further in the proofe of this point: We cannot but confeſſe, that the examples of mercie and comfort in the word, are full of ſtrong &amp; ſound conſolation, becauſe they be as if it were ſo manie ſeales ſet vnto the writings of Gods promiſes, that as heretofore hee hath beene to others, ſo he will hereafter or ſtill, be fauourable vnto his people. And yet wee ſhall ſee, that they lie open though not of themſelues, yet by reaſon of mans corrupted heart to manie exceptions: as for example, they to whom they were accompliſhed were better than wee: God was more fauourable then, than he will be now, becauſe we haue more meanes of mercie, and haue profited leſſe: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore are not ſo properly fit for conſolation, as the promiſes are. For ouer and beſides that they are but in men, and therefore full of weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and wants, wee know and confeſſe euerie where, that as we muſt liue not by examples, but by rules, ſo we muſt bee comforted, not ſo
<pb facs="tcp:11988:34" rendition="simple:additions"/>much by examples, as by promiſes. And ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore though examples be good, yet not ſo ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g; whereas the truths certaintie, and power of the promiſes, is from the might and mercy of him that hath made them, who alſo is both greater then all exception, and free from the leaſt ſhew or ſhadowe of turning. And yet let vs be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood, I beſeech you as we ſhould: namely that wee aſcribe not this excellent worke vnto the promiſes themſelues, though alſo wee deny not but euen in that reſpect, they are ſpirituall, holy, heauenly, &amp;c. but as by the ſpirit they are made powerfull in vs, and as by the hand of faith wee are ſtrengthned to applie them vnto our ſelues: for otherwiſe we may ſay of them, as wee do of the reſt of the word, that without the ſpirit and faith they are as if it were <hi>a ſealed book</hi> vnto vs for vnderſtanding, and <hi>a dead letter</hi> for inſtruction &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſolation, hauing euen no other vſe in vs, than the reſt of the worde not felt or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bayed, namely to make vs without excuſe, or to cauſe our ſorrowefull &amp; heauie eſtate, to beco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e more ſorrowfull and heauie, becauſe wee ſee holy &amp; heauenly thinges propounded vnto vs, and yee haue not either hearts to vnderſtand, or ſoules to beleeue. This therefore muſt be our principall care, to make that profitable vnto vs that GOD graciouſly prouideth and propoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth for our good.</p>
            <p>Now wee come to the vſe of this neceſſarie doctrine, which as I take it, is or may bee two<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folde. Firſt, for inſtruction. Secondly, for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futation.
<pb facs="tcp:11988:35"/>For inſtruction, wee may plainly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue hereby, what is the reaſon of ſo much hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uines of heart, ſorrow, and feare, in ſo manie of Gods people and children in the world. Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly either they are ignorant of theſe ſweet and gracious promiſes not ſo much as hauing either heard them, or knowne them, or els if they haue in ſome meaſure of knowledge beene acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with them, they haue in the careleſſenes of their owne hearts, or not ſeeling preſent vſe of them, let them ſlippe out of their mindes, like leaking veſſelles, not able to containe ſuch good things; or els if they haue knowne them &amp; remembred them thorow want of comfortable feeling of the good things propounded therein, they haue beene vnto them, as if they had either not been at all, or as though they had contained in them, no ſuch ſweetnes and pleaſure as they doe indeed. And let vs not thinke this ſtrange: for euen as ignorance in religion and careleſnes to obey the things that wee know, is a principal cauſe of all tranſgreſſion and looſe life: men not being either willing or able to do the things they are not acquainted withall; and for the things that they know, blearing out their know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>and laying the raines in their owne neckes: ſo they not knowing of the promiſes, or they not minding of them, or not ſtriuing comfortablie to feele them, is the verie welſpring as I maie ſo call it, of all inward and outward diſcomforte, and diſtreſſe of conſcience eſpecially. For how can the wounded conſcience admit comforte,
<pb facs="tcp:11988:35" rendition="simple:additions"/>when he vnderſtandeth not the comfort preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vnto him? or if hee forget it, where is his ioy in the middeſt of his forgetfulneſſe? We ſaie that of an vnknowne thing there is no deſire: &amp; wee maie in proportion ſaie the ſame of a thing that is not remembred. For our owne parts let vs know that as Sathan laboureth to root out of our hearts generally, all the ſeede of the worde, that thereby keeping vs in blindneſſe and igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, hee maie make vs runne riot at his plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure: ſo eſpecially he trauaileth, either to hinder vs from receiuing or hauing receiued from ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king good vſe of the ſweet &amp; comfortable pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes of the worde, the verie matter if I may ſo ſaie, and a ſpeciall meane I am ſure of our ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall comforte. For the redreſſing and repreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing alſo of which enormities in vs, a godly man, that is in ſome ſorte ignorant, ſhould laboure to abound in the knowledge of them: as he that is forgetfull ſhould refreſh his memorie, by of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten reading, meditation and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ference in them, and that not onely by and with his owne heart, but euen by other men alſo: and they that want feeling of them ſhould looke vnto Ieſus Chriſt, <hi>in whom all the promiſes of God are yea and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men,</hi> and ſhould be much and often in the vſe of all the meanes wherby Chriſt is become ours, as the word, ſacraments, praier, ſaſting, &amp;c. But aboue all they ſhould regard, and labour for the holie ſpirit, to be ſhed abroad in their hearts, both to make all theſe things before na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med powerfull in them, and to pledge vp alſo
<pb facs="tcp:11988:36"/>the truth and certaintie of the promiſes them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, becauſe it is the carneſt pennie of our a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doption and inheritance. That ſo ſith ſathan there laboureth to aſſault vs moſt, and ſhake our faith as in that behalfe, wee might thither bring all our aides and defences, as they doe that are in a beſieged hold, and ſo we better made able not onely to indure the aſſault, but to driue our foes with their forces, from our gates &amp; walles. And hee or ſhee or they whoſoeuer that can do this, they maie wel aſſure their hearts, that how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer they maie now &amp; then, or for a while be buffeted &amp; beaten, yet they ſhal neuer be van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſhed or ouercome, becauſe he that is in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; with them &amp; for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, by himſelf &amp; his bleſſed ſpirit, and all other effectuall meanes of conſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and comfort, is ſtronger &amp; greater than al.</p>
            <p>Secondly, it is verie fit and meet for confuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a conceit, that riſeth vp in mens minds, yea &amp; is deliuered alſo by the mouthes of ſome ſpecially our popiſh aduerſaries, who tell vs that this propounding of comfort in the promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of the Goſpell, acquainting the people ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with maketh menſecure &amp; careleſſe. But here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in ſurely they ſhew themſelues blinde &amp; bloc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiſh, as who haue not yet learned to diſtinguiſh betweene a thing good in it ſelfe, and mans cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption abuſing that which is good. They may by the ſelfe ſame reaſon aboliſh all the other parts of the word, and diſanull or euacuate the ſacraments, becauſe infinite thouſands in the world abuſe them, to the increaſe of ſin and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centiouſneſſe
<pb facs="tcp:11988:36" rendition="simple:additions"/>in themſelues: yea if they will or can make fruſtrate Gods grace, becauſe manie turne it into wantonnes, and ſay ſith is this true, that <hi>where ſin hath abounded, there grace hath ſuperabounded, therefore let vs continue in ſinne that grace maie abound?</hi> And if for or in out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward things, we ſhould reaſon as they doe, and haue it followed that ſo is deliuered, we might eaſily bring all diſorder and confuſion into the world, and ouerthrowe the whole courſe and raſe of mankinde. Some abuſe drinke to drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kennes, and other ſome meate to gluttonie and gourmandiſe, therefore there muſt be no vſe of meate and drinke: what is this els but to ſtarue the excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>teſt of Gods creatures, man I meane? Many abuſe apparell to pride, and puffing vp. It were beſt therefore to haue men goe naked, which what were it els but to become or bring in new Adamites? Diuers turne magiſtracy &amp; authoritie into tyrannie, and therefore with the Anabaptiſts, away with all ciuill authoritie and gouerment: which what were it els, but to bring in Anarchie, worſe than tyrannie by much? But to the point indeed. The promiſes of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, and in the ſeruants of GOD bring forth no ſuch effect. For as they are deliuered for the comfort and conſolation of them that are affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted and <hi>mourne in Sion,</hi> as may appeare in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerie place where they are alledged, &amp; namely in the two firſt verſes of the 40. chapter of Iſay, and tend indeede to manifeſt Gods loue and mercy, that ſo in the truth and performance of
<pb facs="tcp:11988:37"/>his word, wee might bee well aſſured, that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſhould put an eternall ſeparatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> between him and vs, that hath loued vs ſo tenderly, and giuen vs ſuch gracious promiſes of truth &amp; life. So ſurely the doctrine euery where adioyned to thoſe promiſes in the word, doth plainely ſhew that God meaneth not, to make men ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure and careleſſe thereby, or would haue them to inferre anie ſuch thing thereupon. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore when in the latter end of the ſixt chapter of the ſecond epiſtle to the Corinth. hee had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged manie promiſes of peace &amp; goodnes, he beginneth the ſeuenth Chapter thus. <hi>Seeing the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wee haue theſe promiſes, dearely beloued, let vs cleanſe our ſelues from all filt hines of the fleſh &amp; the ſpirit, and finiſh our ſanctification in the feare of God.</hi> And the like he doth in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond chapter of the ſecond epiſtle to Timothy, ſaying, <hi>The ſtrong foundation of God remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth ſure, and hath this ſeale, the Lord knoweth who are his: but withall let euery one that cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth vpon the name of Chriſt, depart fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> iniquity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And let this ſuffice for theſe wordes of the 28. verſ. with the reſt I cannot proceed, becauſe we haue been ſomewhat long: and as I am wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie in my ſelfe, ſo am I loath to bee troublous or tedious vnto you. God may be pleaſed hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to giue both occaſion, time and place, to purſue theſe things and to finiſh the reſidue. In the meane while, it ſhall not bee amiſſe, in a word or two to apply that hath been ſaide, to our perſent aſſemblie and cauſes thereof, and ſo
<pb facs="tcp:11988:37" rendition="simple:additions"/>to ſhut vp this exerciſe.</p>
            <p>The cauſes that haue moued vs thereto, are great &amp; grieuous iniquities preuailing vpon al &amp; euery one of vs, the heauie rod of penurie and ſcarſity that ouerfloweth the land, warres and rumors of warres, and the ſame intended and threatned againſt vs, both outward and inward at home and abroad. To diuert or turne away, the puniſhments for our ſinnes and the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments that wee confeſſe and acknowledge, we haue iuſtly deſerued therefore, no outwarde thing will ſerue, though it bee neuer ſo great &amp; glittering or ſeeme neuer ſo pleaſant or paine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, but ſoundnes of heart and humble walking with our God in all our waies, and all the dayes of our liues. To this we haue been exhorted and prouoked by manifolde good meanes, and namely by propounding ſingular comforts and conſolations which the Lord hath vouchſafed vnto vs, the better to meet with our backward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes from approching to him, wee being ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times diſcouraged from doing of that dutie, by his almightie greatnes and excellencie, and ſometimes let from it, by the conſideration of our owne baſe and vnworthie eſtate. But yet ſith hee hath ſo louingly and fatherly called vs, and for our better incouragement giuen vs gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious promiſes, <hi>let vs drawe neere with a true heart in aſſurance of faith, our inward parts be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing pure from an euill conſcience, and waſhed in our bodies with pure water.</hi> And ſo no doubt the puniſhments wee preſently feele ſhal be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mooued,
<pb facs="tcp:11988:38"/>the feare of our foes at home and abroad ſhall be put farre away, and wee ſhall not need to dread the curſes of that Balaam of Rome, not the vaunts and attempts of that proud and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuting notion of Spaine, nor of anie other our enemies bodily or ghoſtly, becauſe that our conſciences being quieted with the comforta. blefeeling of all Gods fauours, and ſpecially of the forgiueneſſe of our ſinnes, and the ſaluation of our ſoules, wee may comfortably ſay, as the ſaithfull that haue gone before vs haue done, <hi>I will not bee afraid for ten thouſand of the people that ſhould beſet me round about. Nay though I ſhould walke in the valley of the ſhadow of death, I will yet feare none ill, for thou art with mee, thy rod and thy ſtaffe, they comforte mee. Yea that wee are perſwaded that neither death, nor life, nor Angels, nor principalities, nor powers, nor things preſent, nor things to come, nor height nor depth, nor any other creature ſhall bee able to ſeparate vs from the loue of God, which is in Chriſt Ieſus our Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now let vs pray that God would giue a rich and plentifull bleſſing in our ſeuerall hearts to al the good things that haue been deliuered vnto vs at this time: and let vs humbly intreat him to make them profitable in vs, not onely for this preſent, but for all the daies of our liues, to his glorie and our euerlaſting comforte thorowe Chriſt.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:11988:38"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
